<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apologetical vindication of the Church of England in answer to those who reproach her with the English heresies and schisms, or suspect her not to be a catholick-church, upon their account.</title>
            <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 229 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43647</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1840</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20398</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12444537</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12444537</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62184</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43647)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62184)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 942:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apologetical vindication of the Church of England in answer to those who reproach her with the English heresies and schisms, or suspect her not to be a catholick-church, upon their account.</title>
                  <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to George Hickes. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62184:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62184:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN Apologetical Vindication OF THE Church of England: IN ANSWER To Thoſe who reproach HER WITH THE ENGLISH HERESIES AND SCHISMS, Or ſuſpect HER not to be a <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> Upon their Account.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s <hi>Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church yard. MDCLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:62184:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62184:2"/>
            <head>THE INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>EVER ſince the Diſſenters left the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and formed themſelves into Separate Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> have not been want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to take advantage from her ſad Misfortune, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe her at home and abroad, as a Church, that amidſt ſo many monſtrous Sects, and ſo many oppoſite and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable Communions, can have no right to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Title of Catholick, nothing really anſwerable to the true Idaea of a Church, nor any pretenſions to the Promiſes of Chriſt, eſpecially thoſe two, of preſerving his Church againſt the Powers of Hell, and of ſending his Spirit of Truth, which is but one, to guide her into all Truth.</p>
            <p>They endeavour to make the World believe, That a Church ſo over-run with Hereſies and Schiſms, and ſo ſhatter'd and torn with inteſtine Diviſions, as ours is, cannot be a true, or good Church; nay, they will ask us by a figure of Reproach, Where they ſhall find her, among ſuch a Crowd of Diſſenters? And thus uſing all manner of Artifice, on the one hand in ſetting forth the many Diviſions in Religion among us, and on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the great Unity in Doctrine and Worſhip among themſelves, they hope to unſettle us yet more, and make our People ſuſpect, or believe, that ours is not a part of the One Catholick and Apoſtolick Church.</p>
            <p>It is now one of their Common Places to talk of our Schiſms, and argue from them upon all occaſions, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> They generally
<pb facs="tcp:62184:3"/>begin there, when they firſt attack any of her Sons, or Daughters; and when ever we engage with them, or they with us, in a Diſpute about the Two Churches, we muſt be content to hear of our Diviſions at both Ears. Sometimes they ſeem to lament them, ſometimes to upbraid us with them, and ſometimes to diſpute down-right upon them; but be their Style and Method never ſo different, when they ſpeak or write of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hereſies and Schiſms, their common Aim and Deſign is the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> to bring us out of conceit with our Church, and perſwade us, that a Church ſo full of imbred Diviſions in Religion, hath not the Characters of Chriſt's Spouſe, no Marks of his Favour, nor any Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude with the Catholick Church, that heavenly <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> which is as a City, that is at peace and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in it ſelf.</p>
            <p>We are told, That it is a ſad thing to conſider, what a world of Hereſies are crept into this Nation, where every man thinks himſelf as competent a Judge of the Scriptures, as the very Apoſtles themſelves—and that that part of the Nation, which looks moſt like a Church, dares not bring the true Arguments againſt other Sects, for fear they ſhould be turned againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Your Church (ſaith another) hath Unity, or not? if not, then ſhe is not the Church of Chriſt? If ſhe hath, why are there ſo many Sects and Schiſms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you? Saith another, who not long ſince was one of her Prieſts, What would I have once given to have found ſuch an Union among <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> nay, to have found one County in my own dear Countrey, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps one ſingle Family, ſo united a Brotherhood.—And in another place he profeſſes, That he cannot tell, how the Church of <hi>England</hi> is able to find her ſelf, in an innumerable Huddle of ten times more Diſſenters, Diſſemblers, (whereof he himſelf was many years
<pb facs="tcp:62184:3"/>one) and Indifferents, than her number is able to make.</p>
            <p>At this rate, and to this purpoſe, they are alſo apt to talk in their private Converſation. For where I live, the Place rings with their Reflections on the Church of <hi>England,</hi> upon the account of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Separations; and having not heard that any thing is yet publiſhed, to help the People to defend themſelves, and the Honour of our Church, againſt them, I thought I could not better ſpend the <hi>Christmas</hi> Vacation, than to write a ſhort Tract, on purpoſe to ſhew, That the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hereſies and Schiſms are in reality no diminution to the Honour of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and that the Conſideration of them, ought to ſcandalize no man againſt her, or make us believe, that ſhe is in any degree leſs Catholick and Apoſtolick, than her greateſt Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers take her to be.</p>
            <p>This is the main Deſign of my preſent Undertaking; and that I may omit nothing of moment, which ought to be ſpoken of ſuch a Subject in ſuch a ſhort Treatiſe, I will proceed in the following Method.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. I will ſhew from Reaſon, and the Hiſtory of the Chriſtian Religion, that all Churches are ſubject to the Misfortune of Schiſms and Diviſions.</item>
               <item>II. That Schiſms and Diviſions, and the conſummati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, in oppoſite Communions, are no good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt the Truth, or Goodneſs, or Reputation of a Church.</item>
               <item>III. That bare Unity, or want of Schiſms and Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Religion, are no ſound Argument for the Truth, or Goodneſs, or Reputation of a Church.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:62184:4"/>
            <p>After I have demonſtrated theſe three Propoſitions, I will make enquiry into the true Cauſes of Schiſms and Diviſions, and more particularly into the Cauſes of theſe in <hi>England:</hi> Then I will ſay ſomething of the Preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Cure of them: And in the Concluſion, make ſuch Addreſſes to the People of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, to the People of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and to the Diſſenters from it, as I hope may become a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and the Author of ſuch a peaceful and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Diſcourſe, as I hope the Reader will find this to be.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62184:4"/>
            <head>AN <hi>Apologetical Vindication</hi> OF THE Church of England.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. I.</hi> Shewing from Reaſon, and the Hiſtory of the Chriſtian Religion, that all Churches are ſubject to the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune of Schiſms and Diviſions.</head>
               <p n="1">1. I Will ſhew from Reaſon, and the Hiſtory of the Chriſtian Religion, that all Churches are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the ſad misfortune of Schiſms and Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to the conſummation of them in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Communions. This, to argue firſt from Reaſon, is as demonſtrable of Eccleſiaſtical, as Civil, or Military Societies, men being as ſubject by their own evil Paſſions, and the Temptations of the Devil, to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny, and make Inſurrections in Churches, as in Camps, or Cities, or other Fraternities of men. Nay it being more for the Intereſt of Satan, and alſo more eaſie to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide a Church, then a Kingdom, or a Camp, men are ſo much the more in danger of being tempted to do the one, rather then the other: and accordingly we find
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62184:5"/>that Churches are more infected with inteſtine Diviſions, then States, and Kingdoms; and whereas formerly one Emperor was able to quell many Mutinies and Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, a ſucceſſion of Chriſtian Emperors ſometimes were not able to quell one Schiſm. Wherefore to purſue my Argument, as Chriſtian Armies are ſubject to Mutinies, becauſe they conſiſt of Souldiers, which may be tempted to Mutiny, and Chriſtian Cities and Kingdoms to Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, becauſe they conſiſt of Subjects, that may be tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to rebel; ſo all Chriſtian Churches are ſubject to Schiſms, and Hereſies, becauſe they conſiſt of Members that may be drawn in to begin, and carry on Hereſie, and Schiſm.</p>
               <p>The Catholick Church, notwithſtanding its holineſs, and all the particular Churches in it, are Bodies politick, that like other Corporations conſiſt of peaceable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaceable, dutiful and undutiful Members; and it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally no ſtranger that a <hi>Diotrephes, Montanus,</hi> or <hi>Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> ſhould prove a Schiſmatick, then that <hi>Judas</hi> ſhould prove a Thief, and a Traitor, or the luſtful <hi>Corinthian</hi> commit Inceſt in the Church of God. What hinders that this or that Member of a Church may not become a Schiſmatick, as well as a Murderer, Drunkard, or Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer? Is it not conſiſtent with the wiſdom of God, or the honour and oeconomy of the <hi>Catholick,</hi> or a <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> Church, to leave the Members of it in a capacity to commit Schiſm?<note place="margin">Fieri vero haec dominus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit, &amp; pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur manent: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priae libertatis arbitrio, ut pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batorum ſides integra manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlâ luce clareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. <hi>Cypr.</hi> de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit. Eccleſ.</note> Doth the nature of a true Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, or hath God any where promiſed to over-rule the free wills of orthodox Chriſtians, ſo that they ſhall not fall into Schiſm, as well as other ſins? Hath he either made them impaſſible, as to this ſingle vice, or reſtrain'd the Devil from tempting them to it? If he hath, let thoſe who upbraid us with our Diviſions ſhew it, and if he hath not, then it muſt follow, that the Clergy and Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all the Churches in the World, being left as free to commit Schiſm, as Rebellion, or any other wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62184:5"/>all Churches whatſoever muſt be ſubject to the ſad misfortune of Hereſie, and Schiſm. The natural Body is not more ſubject to Diſeaſes, then the Body politick of the Church is ſubject to Diviſions: though ſhe have the honour to have Chriſt for her Head, yet is ſhe not exempted from having her Peace broken, or her Unity divided. That is only the priviledge of the Church tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, where Charity is perfected; and therefore to paſs from Reaſon to the Hiſtory of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, we find as many Cautions, and Exhortations in the Scriptures, againſt Hereſies, and Schiſms, as againſt any other mortal ſin. What an excellent Admonition againſt Schiſm did St. <hi>Paul</hi> give the Biſhops and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> or rather all the Biſhops of <hi>Aſia Minor,</hi> aſſembled at <hi>Miletus. Take heed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>unto your ſelves, and to all the flock over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you overſeers,—For I know, that after my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, ſhall grievous wolves enter in among you, not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the flock. Alſo of your ſelves ſhall men ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw away diſciples after them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore watch, and remember that by the ſpace of three years, I ceaſed not to warn every one night and day with tears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtle knew very well, that God in his wiſdom thought it not fit to prevent Hereſies and Schiſms in the moſt Apoſtolical Churches, by his Almighty power, but to ſuffer them as well as other ſins, for the manifeſtation of the good from the bad, and that in ſuch a mixture, as a Church muſt be, they were neceſſary to ſift the Wheat from the Tares, to ſeparate the Gold from the Droſs, and diſtinguiſh thoſe that are ſincere, ſtedfaſt, and genuine Sons of any Catholick Church, from thoſe that are not. Thus in his 1. Ep. to the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> which I ſuppoſe was a very Apoſtolical Church, he tells them, that God thought fit to let Hereſies and Diviſions ariſe among them, that the faith and conſtancy of ſome, and inſtability, vanity, and hypocriſie of others,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62184:6"/>might be made more evident. <hi>I hear</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that when you come together into the Church there are diviſions among you, and I partly believe it, for there muſt be alſo he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies</hi> [or dividing into Sects] <hi>among you, that they which are</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Avolent quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum volent pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leae levis fidei quocun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> afflatu tentationum, co purior Maſſa frumenti in hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reâ domini re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponetur. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull.</hi> de praeſcript. Haer. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>approved, may be made manifest among you.</hi> So ſaith St. <hi>John</hi> of the Antichriſts, which in his time aroſe in the Catholick Church: <hi>They went out from us, but they were not of us, for if they had been of us, they would no doubt have continued with us, but they went out, that they might be made manifeſt that they were not all of us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And our Bleſſed Lord, who was the Founder of the Church, and may be preſumed to have beſt underſtood the nature of it, had no other notion thereof, then as of a Body Corporate, that was ſubject like other Societies, to the great inconvenience of inteſtine Diviſions, and falling into oppoſite Sects and Schiſms. <hi>It muſt needs be</hi> (ſaith he, conſidering the nature and future eſtate of the Church) <hi>that offences come, but wo unto the man by whom the offence cometh.</hi> And in his Sermon on the Mount ſaith he unto his Diſciples, <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets, which come to you in ſheeps-cloathing, but inwardly they are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening wolves.</hi> And in the 24th. Chapter of St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi>'s Goſpel,<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <p>Memores ſimus tam dominicarum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiationum, quàm Apoſtolicarum litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, quae nobis &amp; faturas haereſes praenunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arunt, &amp; ſugiendas praefinierunt. <hi>Tertull.</hi> ibid.</p>
                     <p>Inſtruit dominus multos eſſe venturos ſub pellibus ovium rapaces Lupos. ibid.</p>
                  </note> he foretold the ſad condition of the primitive Church before the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that about that period there ſhould ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, and ſhould ſhew great ſigns, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and deceive, if it were poſſible, the very Elect. This prediction of the Bleſſed Jeſus was fulfilled in the time of the Apoſtles, who were all <hi>infallable Guides</hi> of the Church: for St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his 2. Ep. to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> ſaith, That the myſtery of iniquity was then a working, and the wicked one to be revealed, whoſe coming was after the working of Satan, with all power, and ſigns, and lying wonders, and with all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62184:6"/>to bring them that periſh to commit unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, becauſe they receive not the love of the truth, that they might be ſaved. So St. <hi>Peter</hi> in his 2. Ep. ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, to the Catholick Church, tells the Chriſtians, That as there were falſe Prophets in the Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſo there ſhould be falſe Teachers among them, who ſhould privily bring in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and that many ſhould follow their pernicious ways, by reaſon of whom the truth ſhould be evil ſpoken of. Every one that is verſed in Eccleſiaſtical Story, knows that theſe Apoſtles mean <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus,</hi> who was baptiz'd by <hi>Philip,</hi> and the reſt of the Ring leaders of the <hi>Gnoſtical</hi> Hereſies, who were all Magicians, as well as Hereticks, and wrought won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to prove that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was not the Chriſt. For this Reaſon they are called<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Johannes</hi> in Ep. eos maximè Antichriſtos vocat qui Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum negarent in carne veniſſe, &amp; qui non putarent Jeſum eſſe filium Dei. <hi>Tertull.</hi> de praeſcript. Heret. <hi>33.</hi>
                  </note> Antichriſts by St. <hi>John: Little children,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it is the laſt time, and as you have heard that Antichriſt ſhould come, even now there are many Antichriſts, whereby we know that it is the last time,</hi> of which our Lord ſpoke. And leaſt any ſhould think, that theſe Monſters of Hereſie and Sorcery, which afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the primitive Church, were not Chriſtians, it follows, <hi>They went out from us, but they were not of us, for if they had been of us, they would have continued with us, but they went out, that they might be made manifeſt that they were not all of us.</hi> And ſo in his 2. Ep. ſaith he, <hi>Many deceivers are entred into the world, who confeſs not that Jeſus Christ is come in the fleſh, this is a deceiver, and an Antichriſt; and then knowing in what danger the faithful were,</hi> of being ſeduced by them, ſaith he by way of Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them, <hi>Look to your ſelves, that ye loſe not thoſe things which ye have wrought, but that ye receive a full reward by enduring to the end.</hi> So to ſee the ſad eſtate of the primitive Church more fully out of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, he ſaith in his 2. Ep. to <hi>Timothy, This know that in the laſt days perillous times ſhall come, for men ſhall be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62184:7"/>of their own ſelves, covetous,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>having a form of godlineſs, but denying the power thereof, from ſuch turn away for of this ſort are they which creep into houſes, and lead captive ſilly women,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Now as Jannes and Jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres</hi> [the Aegyptian Sorcerers] <hi>withſtood Moſes, ſo theſe reſist the truth, men of corrupt minds, and reprobate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But beſides the <hi>Simonians,</hi> or Gnoſtick Hereticks, who divided the primitive Church, and formed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into ſeparate Sects, there are evident footſteps in the New Teſtament of many other Diviſions and Schiſms. So <hi>in the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>it ſelf</hi> there were many ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Members, as we find by the words of the Apoſtle: <hi>I beſeech you Brethren</hi> (ſaith he unto the <hi>Romans</hi>) <hi>mark them which cauſe diviſions and offences contrary to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which you have receiv'd, and avoid them, for they that are ſuch ſerve not the Lord Jeſus, but their own belly, and by good words and fair ſpeeches deceive the hearts of the ſimple.</hi> So in his 1. Ep. to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> how often doth he charge them with envying, ſtrife, and diviſions while one ſaid he was of <hi>Paul,</hi> another that he was of <hi>Apollos,</hi> and a third that he was of <hi>Cephas,</hi> or St. <hi>Peter.</hi> So in the Text I cited before, <hi>I hear</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that there be diviſions among you;</hi> and truly theſe Diviſions, notwithſtanding all his Authority and Doctrine to the contrary, were come to ſuch an height, that we find him in the 11th. Chapter uſing the very ſame Apologue for ſubſtance to perſwade the to peace, and unity, and ſubmiſſion to their Superiors, that <hi>Menenius Agrippa</hi> uſed to appeaſe the ſeditious Commons of <hi>Rome,</hi> and perſwade them to return to their obedience to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. <hi>As the Body</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is one, and hath many members, and all the members of that one Body being many, are by union made one Body, ſo alſo is the Church of Chriſt,</hi> with much more to that purpoſe. At the ſame time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62184:7"/>there was many among them, that denied the<note n="*" place="margin">Paulus in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>md ad Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thios not at ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatores, &amp; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitatores reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectionis. Haec opinio propria Sadducaeorum, partem ejus u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpat Marcion &amp; Apelles, &amp; Valentinus, <hi>Tertull.</hi> deprae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript. Haeret. 33.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, or doubted of it, which the <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,</hi> which are ſo ready to note our Schiſms and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, will not deny to be down-right Sadduciſm. Let them hear the Apoſtle arguing againſt it: <hi>If Chriſt be preached that he roſe from the dead, how ſay ſome among you that there is no reſurrection of the dead, for if there be no reſurrection of the dead, then is not Chriſt riſen, and if Chriſt be not riſen, then is our preaching vain, and your faith vain, yea and we are found falſe witneſſes of God.</hi> In his ad. Ep. to them we find him telling them of falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and deceitful workers, that were then among them, who transform'd themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt. Theſe counterfeit Apoſtles had got a mighty eſteem, and intereſt among the people, for it was in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to them that he ſaid, <hi>Ye ſuffer if a man bring you into bondage</hi> [to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Ceremonies] <hi>if a man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour you, if a man take</hi> [money] <hi>of you, if a man exalt himſelf over you, and ſmite you</hi> [as it were] <hi>on the face.</hi> And that they ſhould not think it ſtrange that ſuch fair pretenders to the Apoſtolical Office ſhould be falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>Marvel not at this</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for Satan himſelf is transformed into an Angel of light, and therefore it is no great thing, if his Miniſters alſo be transformed as the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of righteouſneſs.</hi> In his Ep. to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> we find they had thoſe among them, whom the Apoſtle wiſhed out off, becauſe they had perverted the Goſpel with<note n="‖" place="margin">Et ad Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ſcribens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vehitur in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatores &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſores circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifionis &amp; legis: Hebionis haereſis eſt. <hi>Tertul.</hi> ibid.</note> Judaiſm, and ſo bewitched the people with an opinion of the neceſſity of Circumciſion, and other le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Rites, that they had brought them from the Goſpel which the Apoſtle preached, into another Goſpel, which gave him occaſion to ſay, <hi>If we, or an Angel from heaven preach any other Goſpel unto you then that which we have preached, let him be accurſed.</hi> In his Ep. to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> he bids them <hi>beware leaſt any man ſhould ſpoyl them through vain philoſophy, after the tradition of men, after the rudiments
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62184:8"/>of the world, and not after Chriſt;</hi> and prays them to take care, <hi>that no man beguiled them in a voluntary humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and worſhipping of<note n="*" place="margin">Simonianae autem magiae diſcipiina An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelis ſerviens, uti<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> &amp; ipſa inter Idololatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as deputabatur. <hi>Tertull.</hi> de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip. Haeret. <hi>33.</hi>
                     </note> Angles, intruding into thoſe things which he had not ſeen, and vainly puft by his fleſhly mind.</hi> In his 1ſt. Ep. to <hi>Timothy,</hi> he tells him, That <hi>the Spirit ſaith expreſly, that in the latter time ſome ſhall depart from the faith, giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of devils, ſpeaking lies in hypocriſie, having their conſcience ſeared with a hot iron, forbidding to marry, and commanding to abſtain from meats, which God hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be received with thanksgiving, of them which believe and know the truth.</hi> In that Ep. he alſo charged him <hi>to hold the faith, and a good conſcience, which,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſome having put away concerning the faith have made ſhipwrack, of whom is Hymenaeus and Philetus, whom I have deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Satan, that they may learn not to blaſpheme.</hi> And again, <hi>O Timothy, avoid profane and vain bablings, and oppoſition of ſcience falſly ſo called, which ſome profeſſing have erred concerning the faith.</hi> In his <hi>2d.</hi> Ep. to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> we find him complaining in the 1ſt. Chapter, <hi>That all they in Aſia had turned away from him, eſpecially Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellus and Hermogenes.</hi> In the 2d. Chapter he warns him againſt <hi>Hymenaeus and Philetus, who had overthrown the faith of ſome, teaching that the reſurrection was paſt.</hi> And in the laſt we find him complaining of <hi>Demas,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander the Copper-ſmith,</hi> for reſiſting his Apoſtolical Authority, and doing of him much miſchief; and ſo dangerous a Schiſmatick he was, that he did <hi>Timothy</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of him, and pray'd God to reward him according to his works. When he wrote to <hi>Titus,</hi> Hereticks were ſo common in the Church, that he ſaid unto him, <hi>An Heretick after the firſt and ſecond admonition reject.</hi> And in his Ep. to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> we find that there were many among the Primitive Chriſtians, who fell back into Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſm, and embraced Gnoſticiſm, not only after they were illuminated, or baptized, but after they were
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62184:8"/>made partakers by Baptiſm of the miraculous gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, and the Powers of the World to come. They apoſtatized maliciouſly, and out of ſpite to Chriſt forſook the Church; for, as the Apoſtle obſerved, they <hi>did deſpite unto Spirit of Grace, counting the bloud of the Covenant an unholy thing,</hi> whereby they <hi>put him</hi> that ſhed it <hi>to open ſhame, and as it were crucified him afreſh.</hi> I have already obſerved out of the <hi>2d.</hi> Ep. of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> what dangerous and damnable Hereſies there were in his time. I refer the gentle <hi>R.C.</hi> Reader to the <hi>2d.</hi> Chap. of his 2d. Ep. and to the Ep. of St. <hi>Jude,</hi> for a full de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of them, and then will entreat him to tell me, if this Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the midſt of all the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters and their wideſt Doctrines, be in any worſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition then the moſt primitive Catholick Church. I deſire him alſo to accompany me to the<note n="*" place="margin">Johannes vero in Apocalypſi Idolothyta eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; ſlupra committentes jubetur caſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. <hi>Tertull.</hi> in praeſcript, Haeret. <hi>33.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Revelation</hi> of St. <hi>John,</hi> and there I will ſhew him a <hi>Synagogue of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> in the apoſtolical Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and in that of <hi>Sardis</hi> thoſe who <hi>held the doctrine of the Nicolaitans,</hi> and the doctrine of <hi>Balaam, teaching that it was lawful to eat things ſacrificed to idols, and to commit fornication.</hi> The like there were in the Church of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> whom the Spirit ſets forth under the name of <hi>Jezabel.</hi> And in the church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> the mother-Church of them all, there were numbers of counterfeit Apoſtles, which <hi>ſaid they were Apoſtles, and were, not but</hi> upon tryal <hi>were found lyars.</hi> Theſe were all Apoſtolical Churches, and therefore it is a wonder to me, that any man ſhould think it fair and reaſonable to reproach the Church of <hi>England</hi> with the <hi>Engliſh Hereſies and Schiſms,</hi> or to think it ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiſiable to forſake, or undervalue her Communion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account.</p>
               <p>The Church Catholick to this time, and all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Churches in it, were governed by the apoſtles, who undoubtedly had the perſonal gift of Infallibility, or by their Diſciples, and immediate Succeſſors, upon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62184:9"/>whom the Spirit of God was viſible in many<note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>H. E. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 38.</note> miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous gifts, and who were choſen to be Biſhops by the particular<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Clement.</hi> Ep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad Corinth. ed. Oxon. <hi>42.</hi>
                  </note> deſignation of the Holy Ghoſt. I ſay, the whole Church then, and every part of it, was <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Houſe, and God</hi>'s <hi>Building,</hi> and God's Temple, which was built upon the Foundation of the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief corner Stone; and yet we find that God's Husbandry abounded then with Tares, and that his Building, in almoſt all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partments of it, was ſhaken into pieces by Diviſions, even whilſt thoſe Husbandmen and Architects were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, who were Labourers with God, and had the Spirit of God, without which no man ſearcheth the deep things of God. The Church, <hi>with all the Powers which Chriſt leſt unto it,</hi> was not able to ſecure it ſelf from He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies and Schiſms, and an <hi>innumerable huddle of Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;</hi> as is evident from St. <hi>John,</hi> who in his general Ep. to the Church Catholick, bids the Faithful <hi>try the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> before they believed them, <hi>becauſe many falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets were gone out into the World.</hi> And if it were ſo in the green Tree, what muſt it be in the dry? If Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, water'd and planted by the Apoſtles, and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick men, who wrought Miracles, were ſo infeſted with Diviſions, can we expect that Churches planted and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by their Succeſſors at this diſtance, ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from them?</p>
               <p>But let us go on to examine the Apoſtolick Age, and the Ages neareſt unto it, and then we ſhall find that the former Times were not better then theſe. For in the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which was the Mother of all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and the Church wherein St. <hi>Peter</hi> made his firſt Sermon, this primogenial Church, which for<note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>E. H. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> 15 Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions was governed by the<note n="‖" place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>E. H. l.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or Kindred of our Lord, continued no longer<note n="†" place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>E. H. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> undeflowred with Hereſie and Schiſm, then ſhe was under the inſpection of <hi>James,</hi> our Lord's, Brother, who was her firſt Biſhop.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62184:9"/>For when he died, <hi>Simeon</hi> the Son of <hi>Cleophas,</hi> was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to ſucceed him, becauſe he was our Lord's Couſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>german by the Mothers ſide. But<note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>H. E. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Thebuthis</hi> being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended becauſe he was not choſen Biſhop in this vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, began to corrupt the Church, which hitherto had remained a pure Virgin, with vain Doctrines, which he took from the ſeven Sects, of which that of <hi>Simon,</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Magus,</hi> was one, who divided the Unity of the Church, ſaith <hi>Hegeſippus,</hi> by ſtrange adulterous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines againſt God and Chriſt. No Biſhop ever ſuffer'd more by Sectaries, then this good old <hi>Simeon</hi> did in thoſe Times, for without any regard to his pray hairs, who was ſixſcore years old,<note n="‖" place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>E. H. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 33.</note> they accuſed him before <hi>Atticus,</hi> Proconſul of <hi>Syria</hi> under <hi>Trajan,</hi> for being a Chriſtian, and deſcended of the Royal Family of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and ſo procured him, after many Torments, to be put to death.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who was St. <hi>John</hi>'s Scholar, and Biſhop of the Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> wrote Epiſtles to ſeveral Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and in that to the Church of <hi>Smyrna;</hi> we find that there were Hereticks among them, who would not believe that Jeſus Chriſt had a true and real Body, and upon that account abſtained from the holy Euchariſt, and the Prayers of the Church. This Sect, as unreaſonable as it was, was one of the firſt which the Devil ſowed in the field of the Church. St. <hi>John</hi> alluded to it in the beginning of his firſt Ep. general, where he ſaith, <hi>That which was from the beginning, which we have heard, which we have ſeen with our eyes, and which we have looked upon, and our hands have handled of the word of life, that which we have ſeen and heard, declare we unto you, and truly our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> In his Epiſtle to the <hi>Philadelphians,</hi> and <hi>Magneſians,</hi> he complains of the judaizing Chriſtians, who went back from <hi>Chriſt</hi> to <hi>Moſes.</hi> And in his Ep. to the <hi>Tralleſians</hi> and <hi>Philadelphians,</hi> he prays them to abſtain from the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62184:10"/>evil Herbs, which Chriſt did not cultivate, becauſe they were not of his heavenly Father's planting, alluding to the words of our Lord, who ſaid, <hi>Every plant which my heavenly Father hath not planted, ſhall be rooted out.</hi> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore to ſhew what kind of Hereticks and Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks there were in thoſe days, he calls them<note n="*" place="margin">Ep. Ignat. ed. Amſt. p. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> Beaſts in <hi>humane ſhape,</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 21.</note> Beaſts and mad Dogs, which ought to be avoided,<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 26.</note> corrupters of the faith, who ſhould go into unquenchable fire, and<note n="*" place="margin">Ad Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delph.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Wolves in ſheeps cloathing,<note n="†" place="margin">Ad Trall.<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Wolves, that if it were poſſible, would deceive the very Elect.</p>
               <p>About 10 years after the death of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened a moſt<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Clem. ep. p. t.</note> 
                  <hi>ungodly and detestable Sedition,</hi> in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> which occaſioned St. <hi>Clement,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to write that famous Epiſtle to them wherein he tells them, that the Schiſm among them was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a ſhameful, a very ſhameful thing, and unworthy of the name of Chriſtians. And in the <hi>Paſtor of Hermas,</hi> there are alſo manifeſt indications of Faction and Schiſm among Chriſtians when he wrote.<note n="*" place="margin">L. <hi>1.</hi> Viſio <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> Firſt, In his Viſion of the building of the <hi>great Tower upon the Waters,</hi> where by the Stones that had Clefts and Schiſms in them, he underſtands contentious and<note n="†" place="margin">Qui autem ſciſſuras habebant, hi ſunt qui alius adverſus alium in cordibus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiam habent, &amp; non habent pacem inter ſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> quarrelſom Chriſtians, who could not agree together, nor keep the peace of the Church among themſelves, but had heart-burnings one againſt another. Secondly, By the<note n="‖" place="margin">Lapides quos vidiſli longè projectos à turni, &amp; currentes in viâ, &amp; volvi de viâ in loca deſerta, ii ſunt qui crediderunt quidem, dubitatione autem ſuâ reliquerunt viam veram—errant autem &amp; miſeri ſunt ingredientes in deſertas vias.</note> Stones that were ſeen to roul up and down at a great diſtance from the Tower, he underſtands the unſtable ſort of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who having left the Church, miſerably wandred in by-paths, and deſert ways. So in his 8th. ſimilitude of the third Book, he ſets forth four ſorts of men in the Church. Firſt, Thoſe who bring in ſtrange and vain
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62184:10"/>Doctrines into the Church, tho' they do not leave the Communion of it. Secondly, Thoſe who are of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaceable and quarrelſom diſpoſition, and make Feuds in the Church, tho' they do not proceed as far as Schiſm. Thirdly, Thoſe who tho' they keep the right faith, yet through Envy and Emulation, quarrel with one another about Biſhopricks, and Places of Dignity in the Church. And fourthly, Thoſe who apoſtatize from the faith, and ſeparate from the Church.<note n="*" place="margin">Lib <hi>3.</hi> Sim. <hi>8. §. 6, 7.</hi>
                  </note> The firſt ſort were ſet forth by withered Rods, which were not rotten; the ſecond by half withered Rods, in which were clefts; the third by green Rods, in which were clefts; and the laſt by Roads both withered and rotten: And tho' our Adverſaries could ſhew of all theſe ſorts that do, or did belong to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> it is no new, nor extraordinary thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Apol. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>69, 70, 71.</hi>
                  </note> complains grievouſly of the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Hereſies, which to the great prejudice of the Church were taught in his Time. He recites the Names of ſome of the Founders of them, as<note n="‖" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Simon, Menander, Marcion,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Dial. cum Thyph. p. <hi>253.</hi> edit. Pariſ. <hi>1615.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Baſilides, Saturninus;</hi> and tells the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors that they were but nominal Chriſtians, the name of Chriſtian being as common to Sects in Chriſtianity, as that of Philoſopher was to every abſurd Sect in Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy. And in his Dialogue with <hi>Trypho</hi> he ſaith, That the being of Sects and Hereſies confirm'd their faith the more, becauſe they were foretold by our Saviour <hi>in his Parable of the Tares and Wheat;</hi> and where he ſaid, <hi>Falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe; and beware of falſe Prophets which come to you in ſheeps-cloathing, but inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are ravening Wolves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> towards the latter end of the <hi>2d.</hi> Century, wrote an Account of all the <hi>Gnoſtical Hereſies,</hi> ſuch as that of <hi>Simon, Menander, Cerinthus, Carpocrates, Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus, Marcius, Marcion,</hi> the <hi>Ebionites, Valentimans,</hi> and <hi>Colarbaſians,</hi> and others, which in his time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62184:11"/>the Church, ſeducing great numbers with a ſhew of Perfection, and falſe Miracles, eſpecially multitudes of Women, and particularly in his own<note n="*" place="margin">Irenaeus, l.1. c.9.</note> Dioceſs; and yet notwithſtanding all thoſe that went out after thoſe impute Hereſies, <hi>Irenaeus</hi> remained a Catholick and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick Biſhop, and the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, a pure, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, and Apoſtolick Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> wrote againſt the <hi>Valentinians</hi> and <hi>Marcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> and many other Hereſies, in the beginning of the third Century; and becauſe they pretended to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, he wrote a<note n="†" place="margin">Di praeſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>lico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> Book, on purpoſe to ſhew, that the <hi>oldeſt Hereſies</hi> were <hi>later than Truth.</hi> The Church at that time was ſo infeſted with Hereſies, that many<note n="‖" place="margin">Non opritue nos mirari ſuper haereſes iſlas—van<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>è, &amp; in conſideratè pleri<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> hoc ipſo ſcandali <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>antur q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>l tanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n haereſes va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyant—quare ille ſidelſſimi, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ni &amp; uſitatiſion in Eccleſiâ in il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam partem tranſierunt? <hi>Tertull.</hi> ib. <hi>1, 2, 3.</hi>
                  </note> wondred, and were ſcandalized at the number and prevalence of them, and that ſo many eminent men fell and relapſed into them. This gave occaſion to the Father, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of that Book, to tell the <hi>Faithful,</hi> that they were not to take offence, nor won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at the number, or quality of thoſe that forſook the Church. He bid them remember that <hi>Saul</hi> was an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent perſon, before be fell away from God, and that good <hi>David,</hi> and gracious and wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> apoſtatized, the one into Adultery, and the other into Idolatry, and that it was the priviledge only of the Son of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be perfect, and impeccable, and by conſequence it was no Argument for the truth of any Hereſie, tho' a Biſhop, or Deacon, or Doctor, or a holy Widow, or Virgin, or even a Confeſſor, fell into it, becauſe we were not to judge of the Faith by the perſons of men, but of the perſons of men by the Faith. He bid them conſider, That the <hi>Traitor Judas</hi> was an <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> that many of Chriſt own Diſciples forſook him; that <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellus,</hi> and <hi>Hermogenes,</hi> and <hi>Hymenaeus,</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> forſook <hi>Paul;</hi> and that we ſhould not wonder to ſee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62184:11"/>the Church ſo deſerted, and ſuffer after the example of Chriſt. Saith he, They went out from us, becauſe they were not of us; and we ſhould remember the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, who forewarned us of Wolves in ſheeps cloating, of falſe Apoſtles, falſe Prophets, and falſe Teachers, and that Hereſies and Offences would come; and indeed (ſaith he) Hereſies are as neceſſary as Perſecutions, to prove the Faithful, and try who will endure to the end. This Apology which the Father made for the ſad eſtate of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, will, I hope, ſerve as well for ours. I commend it in all humility to the conſideration of the <hi>R. C.s.</hi> eſpecially to <hi>the Miniſter of Putney,</hi> who in his late Book ſeems to take ſo much pleaſure, in twitting us, and our Mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with the <hi>Engliſh Schiſms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to proceed in the Hiſtory of Hereſie and Schiſm. <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> makes the like Apology for the Hereſies of the ſame Age.<note n="*" place="margin">Sero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> p. <hi>753.</hi>
                  </note> He ſaith, They are to Truth, as Tares are to Wheat, that our Lord foretold they muſt come, and that therefore they muſt be; and to ſhew what variety there was then in the Chriſtian World, he reckons up in one<note n="†" place="margin">Strom. l. <hi>7.</hi> p. <hi>765</hi>
                  </note> Page about a dozen ſorts: The <hi>Valentinians, Marcionites, Baſilidiams, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tics, Phrygians, Encratites, Dociles, Haematites, Caj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>iſts, Ophiants,</hi> and <hi>Entychites,</hi> which I think ſould as ill, as <hi>Presbyterians, Independents, Anabaptiſts,</hi> and <hi>Quakers,</hi> with which, I remember, we were reproached not long ſince, in the Colledges of <hi>Navarre</hi> and <hi>Rochell,</hi> in the former with more Raillery, and in the latter with more Zeal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origen</hi> in his Book of<note n="*" place="margin">§.13.</note> Prayer, lately Printed at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> mentions a ſort of Hereticks that rejected Baptiſm, and the Lord's Supper, who, I ſuppoſe, may paſs muſter with our <hi>Quakers,</hi> and another ſort that hold it<note n="†" place="margin">§.14.</note> ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and unprofitable to pray: And in his Anſwer to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62184:12"/>
                  <hi>Celſus,</hi> he makes occaſional mention here and there of moſt of the Hereſies his Time, and ſaith, That<note n="*" place="margin">Lib <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>119.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>5.</hi> p.</note> 
                  <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> who profeſſed to deſpiſe and undervalue Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, becauſe there were ſo many Sects of Chriſtians, muſt for the ſame Reaſon deſpiſe and undervalue Philoſophy and Medicine; for, ſaith he, whatſoever is excellent and profitable for men to know, they will apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſtudy of it, from whence will naturally ariſe divers Queſtions, and divers Opinions, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence divers Sects. For this Reaſon, ſaith he, there are Sects among the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and Sects among the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſome underſtanding the Writing of <hi>Moſe</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in one ſence, and ſome in another, and ſo Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity appearing to be<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> a <hi>great</hi> and <hi>venerable thing,</hi> not only to men of meaner Parts, but to the greateſt Wits among the <hi>Greeks,</hi> they ſet themſelves to the ſtudy of it; and from thence aroſe Sects, <hi>ſome underſtanding the Scriptures, which they all believe, in one ſence, and ſome in another: But yet</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>no man of ſenſe will reject Chriſtianity for that Reaſon, no more then he will reject Medicine or Philoſophy for it, or deſpiſe the holy Books of Moſes and the Prophets for the Hereſies among the Jews.</hi> This (ſaith he) I think, is a ſufficient Apology for the Chriſtian Religion, concerning which I cannot but think of the admirable Saying of St. <hi>Paul, There muſt be Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies among you, that thoſe that are approved may be made manifest.</hi> And therefore (ſaith he again) if the School of Chriſt muſt be diſgraced for the Sects that have come out of it, let the School of <hi>Socrates</hi> be condemned too, becauſe ſo many oppoſite Schools of Philoſophy aroſe out of it; and let the Philoſophy of <hi>Plato</hi> alſo ſuffer the like cenſure, becauſe his Scholar <hi>Aristotle</hi> differ'd ſo much, and in ſo many Opinions from him. This admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Apology the Father made for the Church Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in his Time, and let thoſe who urge <hi>Celſus</hi> his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt us, conſider if it is not as applicable to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62184:12"/>ours. Nay we find by the<note n="*" place="margin">Reſponſ. ad quaeſt. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anſwers to certain Questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> falſly aſcrib'd to <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> that God was pleas'd to allow Hereticks in the primitive Times, to do Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which, praiſed be his holy Name, he never ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any Heretick or Schiſmatick ſince the Reformation to do among us. But if he had, we could have made the ſame defence, which that Author and St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> did <hi>viz.</hi> that Miracles alone, as<note n="†" place="margin">Prophetare, &amp; daemonia excludere, &amp; virtates magnas in terris facere, ſublimis uti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> reseſt, &amp; admirabilis, non tamen— <hi>Cyprian</hi> de unit. Eccleſ. edit. Oxon T. p. <hi>144.</hi>
                  </note> ſplendid gifts as they are, are no demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Truth;</hi> for Chriſt hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that many will ſay unto him in the day of Judgement, <hi>Lord, Lord, have we not propheſied in thy name, and in thy name caſt out devils, and in thy name done many wonderful works?</hi> and then he will reply unto them, <hi>I know ye not, depart from me ye that work iniquity.</hi> So ſaith St. <hi>Paul, Tho' I ſpeak with the tongue of men and Angels, and tho' I have the gift of Prophecy, and underſtand all myſteries, and tho' I have all faith, ſo that I could remove mountains, and have no charity, I am nothing.</hi> The like Apology St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> made againſt the pretended Miracles of the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts:</hi> I hear (ſaith he) that <hi>Pontius</hi> doth Miracles, and that when <hi>Donatus Magnus</hi> pray'd, God anſwered him by a voice from Heaven, but God hath cautioned me againſt thoſe<note n="‖" place="margin">Contra iſtos Mirabiliarios cautum me fecit Deus—<hi>Aug.</hi> Expoſ. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang. Joh. tract. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Miracle-mongers,</hi> who make Diviſions, ſaying, Falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, and ſhall ſhew ſigns and wonders, to deceive, if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, the very Elect, but take ye heed, behold I have foretold you all theſe things. And when his Diſciples told him with joy, that the Devils were ſubject to them in his Name, ſaith he, Rejoyce not in this, that the Devils are ſubject unto you, but that your Names are written in Heaven. Wherefore my Brethren, let no man deceive you, he that works miracles, and doth not keep unity, is nothing. Towards the latter end of the 4th. Century, <hi>Epiphanius</hi> in three Books wrote an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62184:13"/>of all the Hereſies that had been in the Church till that time, and they amount in number to<note n="*" place="margin">Sancti Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanii reſponſ. ad Epiſt. Acacii &amp; Pauli.</note> fourſcore, ſuch a world of Tares grew up with the Wheat from the firſt ſowing of the Word. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath given a compendious Account of all theſe Hereſies out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanius,</hi> and ſome more of his own Time, in a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ad <hi>Quod-vult-Deum.</hi> But ſetting aſide all the reſt, I ſhall only take notice of the <hi>Montaniſts, Novati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Donatiſts,</hi> and <hi>Arians,</hi> which did ſo much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief to the univerſal Church of God, and all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Members thereof.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Montaniſts</hi> pretended to Prophecy, and divine Inſpiration, and tho' they were<note n="†" place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>H. E. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 15, 16, 18, 19.</note> reſiſted by many brave Biſhops, and many learned men wrote againſt them, yet they ſpread their Infection far and near, and<note n="‖" place="margin">Epiphan. <hi>vol.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 416.</note> perverted all <hi>Phrygia, Cappadocia,</hi> and <hi>Cilicia,</hi> and afterwards their corrupt Doctrine went Weſtward, as far as <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> it ſelf.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Novatian</hi> Schiſm began in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, and was ſo called from <hi>Novatus,</hi> whom the Greek Writers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found with <hi>Novatianus,</hi> a Presbyter of that Church. He<note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 43.</note> taught, that it was not lawful to admit thoſe who had fallen in the <hi>Decian</hi> Perſecution, upon their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to communion with the Faithful, and getting himſelf ordained Biſhop in a ſiniſter manner, he drove many under that pretence from the Church, and then there was <hi>Biſhop</hi> againſt <hi>Biſhop, Church</hi> againſt <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Altar</hi> againſt <hi>Altar,</hi> even at <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf. Neither <hi>Cartwright,</hi> nor <hi>Travers,</hi> nor any other Presbyter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> did ever do her ſo much miſchief, as <hi>Novatus</hi> did the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Schiſm which he raiſed, laſted 200 years, and had not <hi>Cornelius</hi> been well aſſiſted by the Catholick Biſhops, not only in <hi>Italy,</hi> but over all the Chriſtian World, this peſtilent Schiſm, under the pretence of greater Purity, would ſoon have driven him out of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62184:13"/>
               <p>The Schiſm of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> firſt began in <hi>Carthage,</hi> and they were ſo called from <hi>Donatus Caſenſis,</hi> the Head of the Party, which firſt erected Altar againſt Altar in that metropolitical City, ſetting up <hi>Majorinus</hi> againſt <hi>Cecilian,</hi> who was rightfully ordained Biſhop of that Church. Of all the Schiſms upon record, this was one of the moſt unreaſonable, diſhonourable, ſtubborn, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, and bloudy, as will appear from this ſhort Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof.</p>
               <p>Firſt, It was very unreaſonable, becauſe it was made by a Party, which had nothing to object againſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Diſcipline, or Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>Carthage,</hi> but only againſt the Canonical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacity of <hi>Cecilian</hi> to be Biſhop of it, as one who was a <hi>traditor,</hi> and worſhipper of Idols in the <hi>Diocleſian Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,</hi> which notwithſtanding appear'd upon many Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als to have been a malicious Accuſation, nothing of this having been laid to his charge, when he was elected and ordained.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It was a moſt diſhonourable and ſhameful Schiſm, as having been begun and carried on by a rich proud and inſolent<note n="*" place="margin">Lucilla.</note> Woman, who was obnoxious to the Rod of <hi>Cecilian,</hi> and corrupted <hi>Secundus</hi> the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of <hi>Numidia,</hi> and many other <hi>African</hi> Biſhops, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Faction againſt him, together with thoſe ſacrilegious Presbyters, whom <hi>Cecilian</hi> had called to account for the Plate, and other Goods of the Church, which had been committed to their Truſt in the time of the Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It was a moſt ſtubborn and prevalent Schiſm, which would not yield nor ſubmit to the Autority of the Emperor, the Sentence of two<note n="†" place="margin">Romanun: &amp; Arelatenſe.</note> Councils, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of the Proconſul of <hi>Africa,</hi> nor the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the univerſal Church. On the contrary, the more it was condemned, it grew the more inſolent, and powerful, and oppreſſed not only the Church of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62184:14"/>where it firſt began, but made almoſt the whole Church of <hi>Africa</hi> revolt.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, It was a moſt impudent Schiſm, the Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks eſteeming themſelves as the only pure People of the World, and the Catholicks as Pagans and Idolaters, plundering their Churches, burning their Altars as pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, and treading their holy Sacraments, which they found upon them, under their feet. They alſo denied them Chriſtian Burial, and re-baptized and re-confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as many of them as revolted to them, and truly ſo general was the Revolt in all Parts of <hi>Africa,</hi> that the Catholick Communions looked more like Conventicles, then the Catholick Church.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, It was a moſt bloudy and cruel Schiſm, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the Feats of the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>So called,</hi> quod circum cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las vagantur. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> T. <hi>7.</hi> p. <hi>76.</hi> G. T. <hi>8.</hi> p. <hi>334.</hi> M. T. <hi>8.335.</hi> D. E.</note> 
                  <hi>Circellians,</hi> or <hi>Circumcellians,</hi> whom the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> called <hi>Agoniſtici,</hi> becauſe they fought for them, and deſtroyed the Catholicks in a moſt barbarous manner. For they were the<note n="†" place="margin">Habebant Donatiſtae per omnes penè Eccleſias ſuas perditum hominum genus perverſum, ac violentum, velut ſub profeſſione continentium ambulantes qui Circumcellio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dicebantur, &amp; erant ingenti numero, à turbâ per omnes ferè Africanas regiones con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituti, qui malis imbuti doctoribus, auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, ſuperbiâ, &amp; termeritate illicitâ, nec ſuis, nec alienis aliquando parcebant, contra jus, faſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in cauſis interdicentes hominibus, &amp; niſi obediſſent damnis graviſſimis, &amp; caedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus afficiebant, armati diverſis telis, bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantes per agros villaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad ſanguinis effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem accedere non metuentes—into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berabiles perſecutiones unitati Eccleſie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacti faciebant, ipſiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſacerdotibus Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis &amp; miniſtris aggreſſiones nocturnas at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que diurnas, direptioneſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> rerum omnium vi inſerebant. Nam &amp; multos dei ſervos caedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bus debilitaverunt—<hi>Poſſidonius</hi> in vit. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Vid. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Ep. <hi>48.</hi> &amp; <hi>50.</hi> De Haereſibus ad Quod-vult-deum? Ep. <hi>68.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra <hi>Creſcon.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> Enarrat. in <hi>Pſ. 10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Zealots</hi> of the Faction, who thought they did God good ſervice in making havock of the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> nay they were ſuch furious Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſts, that when they had none to kill, as St. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaith, they would kill themſelves. They laid wait for the <hi>Catholicks</hi> in the ways, and murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both the Clergy and the People, they took them out of their Houſes by force, to kill them, they beat them to death with Clubs, poured Lime and Vinegar into their Eyes, plundered and burnt their Houſes, and murdered Biſhops and Prieſts at the very Altar, and marched about day and night doing theſe horrible Exploits, under the conduct of <hi>Donatiſt</hi> Biſhops and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62184:14"/>Prieſts. Nay the whole Sect was all Cruelty and Pride, for a <hi>Catholick</hi> no ſooner turned <hi>Donatiſt,</hi> but he alter'd his temper, and became impatient, furious, haughty and contentious, and indeed the many Maſſacres and Deva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations the whole Party committed, ſhews they delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Cruelty and Bloud. Such was the Schiſm of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and it deſerves to be well conſidered by thoſe, who are apt to make uncharitable Reflections upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or have a mean opinion of her Communion upon the account of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Schiſms.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Arian</hi> Schiſm firſt began in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and had its Name from <hi>Arius,</hi> a Presbyter of that Church. At the firſt broaching of his Hereſie, he was oppoſed by <hi>Alexander</hi> his Biſhop, and part of the Clergy and People adhering to the Biſhop, and part ſiding with <hi>Arius,</hi> from this ſmall ſpark, ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Socrates,</hi> came ſuch a fire, as made a Conflagration in the univerſal Church. Firſt, It enflamed the Churches of <hi>Aegypt, Lybia,</hi> and the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Thebais,</hi> and from thence was blown into all the other Churches, when, as<note n="†" place="margin">De vit. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>62.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> writes, one might have ſeen not only Biſhops contending with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but the People rent into Factions, ſome inclining to this Party, and ſome to that, and when the Pagans alſo took advantage from thoſe Diviſions of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to expoſe Chriſtianity in their Theatres, and turn it into ridicule.</p>
               <p>This ſad eſtate of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church, drew tears from the eyes of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and moved him to call the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> to compoſe this Difference, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not much leſs, about a matter of far leſs moment, which had riſen between the Eaſtern and Weſtern Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, about no greater matter then the obſervation of <hi>Eaſter.</hi> day.</p>
               <p>The unanimous Decree of the Council againſt <hi>Arius,</hi> and his Doctrine backed with the Autority of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, did for the preſent ſilence the <hi>Arian</hi> Controverſies;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62184:15"/>but his Son <hi>Conſtantius</hi> turning <hi>Arian,</hi> it broke out with more fury then formerly, and cauſed ſo much Sedition and Bloudſhed in Chriſtian Cities, eſpecially about the<note n="*" place="margin">Socrat. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, 6, 7, 11, 12, 13, 16, 28.</note> choice of Biſhops, and ſo many Subdiviſions in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons among the <hi>Arians</hi> themſelves, that one may well wonder, how ever Chriſtendom came to be at peace and unity again. Then not only Biſhops were divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Biſhops, but Councils contradicted Councils. Then were made at ſeveral Times and Places, no leſs than nine Forms of Confeſſion, moſt of them differing from one another, and all from the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed. Nay then not only the <hi>Arians</hi> were divided among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but the Orthodox, about the manner of receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the convert <hi>Arians</hi> into Communion,<note n="†" place="margin">Fauſtin. &amp; Marcell. lib. precum ad im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Val. Theodoſ. &amp; Arcad. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Lucifer</hi> and his Party ſtanding upon ſtricter terms then the reſt. I have given this ſhort Account of the <hi>Arian</hi> Schiſm, to ſhew how not onlyh this and that Church, but the whole Catholick Church, may at one time labour under Schiſm. And upon making particular enquiry into particular Churches, we ſhall find how in many of them there was Biſhop againſt Biſhop, Altar againſt Altar, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion againſt Communion, which made <hi>Julian</hi> the Emperor ſcoptically ſay, That the Son of <hi>Mary</hi> had now verified his own Saying, that he came not to ſend Peace upon the Earth, but a Sword.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Alexandria</hi> there were two oppoſite Churches owning two oppoſite Biſhops; the Orthodox, who ſtill adhered to <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> preſent, or abſent, and the <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who received <hi>Gregory,</hi> and <hi>George,</hi> and the reſt that were put in his Place.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Antioch</hi> there were at one time three oppoſite Churches; one of the <hi>Arians,</hi> of which <hi>Euzoius</hi> was Biſhop, one of converted <hi>Arians,</hi> of which <hi>Meletius</hi> was Biſhop, and one of thoſe who never ſell into <hi>Arianiſm,</hi> of which <hi>Paulinus</hi> was Biſhop, and yet the divided ſtate of Chriſtendom at this time, was no offence, or wonder
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62184:15"/>to a wiſe Pagan, I mean the Philoſopher <hi>Themiſtius,</hi> who in a<note n="*" place="margin">Socrat. <hi>H E. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 32.</note> Speech which he ſpoke to the Emperor <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens,</hi> to perſwade him to moderate his cruel Perſecution of the Orthodox, told his Majeſty, That he ought not to admire at the diſagreement of Opinions among the Chriſtians, which was but ſmall, if compared with the multitude and confuſion of Opinions among the <hi>Greeks,</hi> among whom there were above 300 different Sects. Nay he pray'd him to conſider, that the moſt excellent and uſeful Arts had never arrived to ſuch perfection, but by difference of judgement, and ſtrife among the Artiſts themſelves; nay that Philoſophy, the Mother of all good Arts, had riſen from ſmall beginnings, to ſuch a height of perfection, by differences among learned men.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and in many other Cities, there were formed Churches of <hi>Arians</hi> and <hi>Novatians,</hi> under their reſpective Biſhops, oppoſite to one another, and both in oppoſition to the true Catholick Church. From this toleration of ſeparate and oppoſite Churches, aroſe many<note n="†" place="margin">Socrat. <hi>H. E. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> Differences,<note n="‖" place="margin">Id. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> Tumults, Quarrels, and Blound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, as when the <hi>Arians</hi> aſſembled in the <hi>Piazz's of Conſtantinople</hi> by night, and from thence went through the Streets of the City, ſinging alternative Hymns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe <hi>who believed three to be one Power. Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom,</hi> the Catholick Biſhop, fearing leſt the People might be drawn from the Church by ſuch Hymns, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points ſome of the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> in oppoſition to the <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> to go about ſinging nocturnal Hymns againſt their Opinions, upon which the<note n="*" place="margin">Socrat. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> two Parties meeting one another, and being more willing to fight then to ſing, they fell to violence, and in the Conflict many on both ſides were wounded, and ſome ſlain.</p>
               <p>Nay in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, which now boaſts ſo much of its Unity under one Head, in <hi>Rome</hi> the pretended Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Chriſtendom, there have been as ſhameful, wide, and violent Schiſms, as any were ever in the Chriſtian
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62184:16"/>World, Schiſms<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Socrat. <hi>E. H. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 29.</note> not upon the account of any pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Hereſie, or diſlike of Ceremonies, nor conſiſting in a ſeparation of the Clergy and People from the Biſhop, but Schiſms of a more dangerous and ſcandalous nature, betwixt <hi>Rival Popes</hi> and their Parties, when there were ſeveral Pretenders to the Chair of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and ſome adhered to this Pope, and ſome to that. Thus in the Reign of <hi>Valentinian,</hi> upon the death of Pope <hi>Liberius,</hi> the Clergy and People of <hi>Rome</hi> were divided in the choice of a Biſhop to ſucceed him. The holy part of the People which adhered to <hi>Liberius</hi> in his Baniſhment, againſt the perjured and uſurping Pope <hi>Felix,</hi> being convened by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus, Amantius,</hi> and <hi>Lupus,</hi> choſe<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Alias</hi> Urſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus,</hi> but the perjured part of the Clergy, which broke the ſolemn Oath they had made, not to chooſe a Biſhop during the Baniſhment of <hi>Liberius,</hi> and that part of the People which adhered to them, choſe <hi>Damaſus</hi> Biſhop, who was one of thoſe who broke his faith with <hi>Liberius. Urſinus</hi> was ordain'd Biſhop by <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bur,</hi> and <hi>Damaſus</hi> was ordained by others in the <hi>Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> Church, and part of the Clergy and People adhered to one, and part or the other, with very great Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities on both ſides. Where was the Unity of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Communion, when the <hi>Roman Church</hi> had two op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Popes, and the People were divided into two ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate Chruches under them? <hi>Damaſus</hi> indeed prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not by the merits of his Cauſe, or that he had the better claim, but by bribing the Courtiers, and great men of <hi>Rome,</hi> and intrigueing with the<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>He was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> Matrona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Auriſcalpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> Matrons of the City, and ſo procuring the Baniſhment of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus,</hi> who was choſen by the faithful and holy part of the People, which ſuffer'd their bloud to be ſhed for him, and the juſtice of his Cauſe, and after his Baniſhment owned themſelves to be his Flock, and refuſed communion with <hi>Damaſus,</hi> believing him to be the rightful Pope. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſus</hi> from the firſt was ſo enraged againſt them, that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62184:16"/>he hired the Rabble to outrage them; they made a great ſlaughter of them for three days together at the Temple of <hi>Julius,</hi> then in the Church of <hi>Sicininus,</hi> called alſo the Church of <hi>Liberius</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid</hi> Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lini <hi>hiſt. l.</hi> 27. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note>, where they killed an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixty, and wounded very many more, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a great part died of their Wounds. But all this did not deter them from meeting together, but three days after they aſſembled again, reciting againſt <hi>Damaſus</hi> thoſe words of our Lord, Fear not thoſe who can kill the body, but are not able to kill the ſoul. Then they ſang out of the <hi>Pſalms, The dead bodies of they ſervants have they given to be meat unto the fowls of the air, and the fleſh of thy ſaints unto the beaſts of the field, their blond have they ſhed like water on every ſide of Jeruſalem, and there was no man to bury them.</hi> And often meeting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the Church of <hi>Liberius,</hi> they cryed out, O Chriſtian Emperor! let all the Biſhops meet at <hi>Rome,</hi> let them try the Cauſe between <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus</hi> and <hi>Damaſus,</hi> and drive the Murderer from St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Chair.</hi> Theſe Complaints of the People coming to the ears of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, he called back <hi>Urſinus</hi> from Baniſhment; the People met him with great joy, but <hi>Damaſus</hi> by bribing the Court gets him baniſhed again. After this, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited the Biſhops of <hi>Italy</hi> to a Feaſt upon his Birth-day. Some of them came, whom he would have perſwaded both by good words and money to depoſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus,</hi> but they deſired to be excuſed, telling him, that they came to celebrate his Birth-day, and not to condemn a man unheard.</p>
               <p>This Account which I have given of the Schiſm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Damaſus</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus,</hi> is taken our of the Preface of <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Presbyter, and <hi>Fauſtinus</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Deacon, before the <hi>Libellus precum,</hi> or humble Supplication, which they preſented to the Emperors, <hi>Valentinian, Theodoſius,</hi> and <hi>Arcadius.</hi> I refer the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to it in the<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>A. D.</hi> 1628</note> 
                  <hi>Oxford</hi>-Edition of <hi>Fauſtinus,</hi> and if he
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62184:17"/>pleaſe to conſult it there, he will find all that I have written, and ſome more remarkable paſſages, which, for brevity ſake, I thought fit to omit. I know very well that <hi>Baronius</hi> hath ſaid all he can to render this Account ſuſpected, becauſe it invalidates the Title of <hi>Damaſus,</hi> and interrupts the lawful Succeſſion to St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s <hi>Chair.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, He pleads that <hi>Marcellinus</hi> and <hi>Fauſtinus</hi> were Hereticks, and that their teſtimony is no more to be believed, then the teſtimony of Thieves againſt thoſe they have robbed. But was the <hi>Luciferian Hereſie,</hi> ſo called, an Hereſie indeed?<note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt. de Hereſ, ad Quodv. Luciferianos a Larcifero Carali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tano Epiſcopo exortos, &amp; cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riter nominatos, nec Epiphanius, nec Philaſter inter hereticos poſuiticredo tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tummodo ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, non haereſin eos condidiſſe, credentes.</note> St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> obſerves, that neither <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> nor <hi>Philaſtrius,</hi> put the <hi>Luciferians</hi> in the number of Hereticks, and is very willing to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them from Hereſie. Or if it were a Hereſie, was it of ſuch a nature as to deprave and infatuate the Souls of men, and to deprive them at once both of truth and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe, in making of them write a heap of Lyes to the Emperor, while <hi>Damaſus</hi> was alive, with many more eye-witneſſes of the Schiſm, whom they might conclude would have publickly expoſed their Account, if it had been falſe? Was not <hi>Lucifer</hi> himſelf a very holy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Perſon, notwithſtanding the ſeverity of his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and a great Champion of the Church againſt the <hi>Arians,</hi> and might not thoſe who ſtood up with him for the ſtrictneſs of Church-diſcipline, and purity of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, out of hatred to <hi>Arianiſm,</hi> notwithſtanding their excuſable error, be as holy men as he? I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent no unprejudiced man, that will obſerve what an excellent ſtrain of Piety and Zeal runs through their Works, can ſuſpect them capable of writing ſuch groſs Forgeries, as the Preface indeed contains, if it be not true.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Baronius</hi> objects, that they aſſert <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus</hi> to have been ordained Biſhop before <hi>Damaſus,</hi> contrary to St. <hi>Hierom</hi> in his <hi>Chronicon,</hi> who ſaith, that <hi>Damaſus</hi> was
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62184:17"/>ordained firſt. But by his favour, their words in the Preface do not neceſſarily import ſo much, as the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Annotator in the <hi>Oxford</hi> Edition hath obſerved; but if they did, why is not their Teſtimony as good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> as St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s is againſt theirs? and why may not he be ſuppoſed to have ſtrain'd a little in favour of his Maſter <hi>Damaſus,</hi> who had ſo obliged him, as well as they, to have prevaricated out of hatred to him?</p>
               <p>secondly, He oppoſes the Autority of <hi>Ruffinus</hi> againſt them, who relates the Story in favour of <hi>Damaſus.</hi> But was not <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> as learned men obſerve, a very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and oſcitant Hiſtorian? How many Miſtakes doth the learned <hi>Valeſius</hi> obſerve in his Hiſtory, in his Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations upon <hi>Socrates?</hi> and which is it moſt reaſonable to believe; an unaccurate man, that writes by hear ſay, and at a diſtance, and in a general Hiſtory: or men that with great accuracy write of any Fact, which they had all the means of knowing exactly, and could not, unleſs they would wilfully, miſtake.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, He moſt frigidly objects, that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus</hi> muſt needs have been the ſchiſmatical Biſhop, becauſe he was ordained by the Biſhop of <hi>Tibur,</hi> and not of <hi>Oſtia,</hi> to whom, he ſaith, it did belong to ordain the Biſhops of <hi>Rome.</hi> It is true, it was the cuſtom of the Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans and Patriarchs, to be ordained by ſome of their neighbouring com-provincial Biſhops, as St. <hi>Aug.</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, in defence of <hi>Cecilian</hi>'s Ordination againſt the <hi>Donatiſts,;</hi> and this he proves by the example of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Oſtia,</hi> who uſually ordained the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> But what tho' that Biſhop did uſually ordain the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops,<note place="margin">Non expectaverit Cecilianus ut princeps à principe ordinaretur, cum aliud habeat Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Catholicae conſuetudo, ut non Numidiae, ſed propinquiores Epiſcopi Epiſcoporum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Carthaginis ordinent: ſicut nec Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae Ecclieſiae ordinat aliquis Epiſcopus Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitanus, ſed de proximo Oſtienſis Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus, <hi>Aug.</hi> in brev. collat. di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 32.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.3.</note> doth it follow from thence, that he was Judg of their election, and that if the See was vacant, or the Biſhop of it ſick, or abſent, or ſuperannuated, and could
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62184:18"/>not, or had no mind, and would not do that office, that another, for example, the biſhop of <hi>Tibur,</hi> might not do it as well? Some of theſe perhaps might be the Caſe when <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus</hi> was elected: for we do not read that the Biſhop of <hi>Oſtia</hi> ordained <hi>Damaſus;</hi> or if he had for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ordained him, might not <hi>Damaſus</hi> have corrupted him, as well as the Courtiers and Magiſtrates of <hi>Rome,</hi> or Preface ſaith he would have engaged the Biſhops of <hi>Italy</hi> to condemn <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus?</hi> and methinks if his had been the juſter Cauſe, he ſhould for his reputation have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the hearing of the whole Matter to a Council of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and got him and his Party condemned, as <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> got <hi>Novatus</hi> and his: but this he never did, which is no ſmall preſumption, that his Election was not ſo ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiable, and his Right ſo clear, as <hi>Baronius</hi> would have it to be. But whether it were or no, doth not directly concern my preſent Deſign, which is chiefly to ſhew, what a violent, dangerous, and ſcandalous Schiſm this was, which happened in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. It was ſo violent, that according to<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>treplerentur humano ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne orationum lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</note> 
                  <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> and the <hi>Greek</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians, out of whom I might have deſcribed it, it cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a great deal of Bloudſhed in Churches; ſo dangerous, that the Souls of many on the one ſide or other muſt needs have miſcarried in it; and ſo ſcandalous, that it gave oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to a<note n="†" place="margin">M. Marcelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in loco ſupra citat.</note> Pagan Hiſtorian to make ſuch Reflections, as I wiſh, for the honour of the <hi>Roman</hi> See, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Epiſcopal Office, had never been made. It happened in the year 366, and after the death of Pope <hi>Zoſimus,</hi> there happened another ſcandalous and horrible Schiſm, between <hi>Boniface</hi> and <hi>Eulalius,</hi> in the year 419, which cauſed ſuch great and dangerous Tumults in the City, that <hi>Honorius</hi> the Emperor, who was then at <hi>Milan,</hi> was not without apprehenſions what might be the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of it, and therefore to prevent and all preſent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, commanded both of them to be put out of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:62184:18"/>To paſs over many intermediate Schiſms in after Ages, there happened many more of a very ſcandalous nature, between contradictory Popes aſſiſted by contradictory Parties and Councils, who could not agree about the rightful Pope. Thus in the year 891, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was miſerably divided between <hi>Formoſus</hi> and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius,</hi> who were both choſen in <hi>Rome</hi> by different Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and tho' <hi>Formoſus</hi> prevailed, yet <hi>Stephen</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi> his next Succeſſor but one, abrogated and nulled all his Orders, and degraded all whom he had ordained, and gave them new Orders. In the year 965. there happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a great Schiſm after the death of <hi>John</hi> the 12th. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Benedict</hi> the 5th. and <hi>Leo</hi> the 8th. <hi>Platina</hi> could not determine which was the right Pope, but puts them both in his Lives; but <hi>Onuphrius,</hi> in his Annotations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Life of <hi>Benedict,</hi> and in his Eccleſiaſtical Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology, faith expreſly, that <hi>Benedict</hi> was the Schiſmatick, and <hi>Leo</hi> the lawful Pope.<note n="*" place="margin">In anno <hi>965.</hi> Tom. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Baronius</hi> is of the contrary opinion; he makes <hi>Leo</hi> the Antipope, and <hi>Benedict</hi> the Pope; and<note n="†" place="margin">In Chron. p. <hi>827.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Genebrard</hi> confeſſes, that their Hiſtorians are not agreed which of the two was the rightful Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor to St. <hi>Peter's Chair.</hi> In the year 1080, the whole Peace of Chriſtendom was diſturbed by the Schiſm, which happened betwixt <hi>Clement</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> and <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7th. 8th. and <hi>Gelaſius</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> and <hi>Gelaſius</hi> dying, it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed between <hi>Clement,</hi> and <hi>Calixtus</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> who was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen in the room of <hi>Gelaſius.</hi> The Emperor was for <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> were for <hi>Calixtus,</hi> tho' the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy and People were much divided in their opinions, ſome maintaining the one, and ſome the other, and ſome again that neither Party was duly elected: but <hi>Calixtus</hi> having taken his Rival priſoner by the help of a good Army put an end to that Schiſm. After the death of <hi>Adrian</hi> the 4th. in the year 1159, happended a grievous Schiſm, betwixt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62184:19"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Maximum Eccleſiae Schiſma oriri coepit quod xix annls miſerabiliter duravis, <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Friſing. Chron.</hi> Lib. 7. Cap. ult.</note> 
                  <hi>Victor</hi> the 4th, and <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> which for 19. years mightily di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed the Chriſtian World, ſome of the<note n="†" place="margin">Cardinales in ſeditionem converſi gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ electione ſcindunt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitatem. <hi>Radevic. Friſingenſis.</hi> L. <hi>2.</hi> C. <hi>43.</hi>
                  </note> Cardinals choſe the one, and ſome the other, and after their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective elections both were ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſent out<note n="‖" place="margin">Id. I. <hi>2.</hi> C. <hi>50. 51.</hi>
                  </note> Circular Letters with contradictory proteſtations and remonſtrances, atteſting God to the truth of what they ſaid. <hi>Alexander</hi> called God to witneſs in his Letters, that he was choſen by all the Cardinals but three, and yet the Cardinals of <hi>Victor</hi>'s Party in a<note n="*" place="margin">Radevic. Friſing. <hi>L.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 51.</note> publick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration proteſt that he was choſen by nine Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals.</p>
               <p>The Emperour, to put an end to this Schiſm, calls a Council at <hi>Pavia,</hi> and to that end wrote to <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and the Cardinals, and alſo to the <hi>Tramontan</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to meet there. The<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 64, 65, 66, 67.</note> Council being met, the Emperour made a ſpeech to them, to exhort them with Faſting and Prayers to commend the Cauſe of the Church to God, and after ſeven days diſcuſſion of the Controverſy between the two Popes, they gave ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in behalf of <hi>Victor,</hi> and the Canons of St. <hi>Peter</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> in a Letter to the Emperor and the Council, did aſſure them, that the uncorrupt and better part of the Cardinals were for him; whereupon the Emperor ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and confirmed his Election, and by his Edict com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded he ſhould be received as Pope. He died after he had ſate four years, and was ſucceeded by <hi>Paſchal</hi> the <hi>3d. Calliſtus</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> and <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> all oppoſite Popes to <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> whom the <hi>Roman</hi> Writers affirm to have been the true Pope. But the moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Schiſm of all the reſt, was that which began in the year 1378. between <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the 6th. and <hi>Clement</hi> the 7th.<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> kept his Seat at <hi>Rome,</hi> but <hi>Clement</hi> at <hi>Avignion,</hi> and the <hi>Germans, Hungarians, Engliſh,</hi> and part of <hi>Italy,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:62184:19"/>ſtood for the former, and the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> for the latter: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> created 54 Cardinals, and <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> 36.</p>
               <p>The Schiſm between theſe two Popes and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, laſted about 50 years, or according to<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſtory of Popiſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Mr. <hi>Foulis</hi> (who accounts the Schiſm of <hi>Felix</hi> againſt <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genius</hi> as a part of it, becauſe it ſprung from it) above 70 years, during all which time, excepting the interval between <hi>Clement</hi> and <hi>Felix</hi> the 4th. there were two op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Lines of Succeſſion to St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Chair,</hi> till <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix,</hi> whom the Council of <hi>Baſil</hi> ſet up againſt <hi>Clement,</hi> upon the earneſt entreaty of the Emperor, reſigned up all his Intereſt to the Popedom, and left <hi>Nicolas</hi> the 5th. Succeſſor in the Line of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban,</hi> ſole ſoveraign Pontif in the <hi>Roman</hi> Throne. Nay during the time of this Schiſm, there were ſometimes three Popes; for the Cardinals thinking to end the Schiſm, called a Council at <hi>Piſa,</hi> where they depoſed <hi>Gregory</hi> the 12th. one of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi>'s Succeſſors, and <hi>Benedict</hi> the 11th. one of <hi>Clement</hi>'s Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, and choſe <hi>Alexander</hi> the 5th. who died before he had ſate a year. <hi>Alexander</hi> was ſucceeded by <hi>John</hi> the <hi>23d.</hi> who created 16 Cardinals, and ſate ſeven months, till the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> perſwaded him to recede, and become a private man again. A man would think, that of all Chriſtians in the World, a <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> ſhould be moſt backward to upbraid the Church of <hi>England</hi> with Schiſm, conſidering what fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and violent Schiſms his own Church hath laboured under in former Ages; Schiſms that have rent the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſplit, if not interrupted the Line of Succeſſion in the <hi>one Catholick Church,</hi> and brought it to ſuch a ſad condition, that the ſecular Authority has been fain to determine of two or three Popes, which was rightfully elected, and which not. Thus in the Reign of<note n="†" place="margin">2, &amp; 3 <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>A.D.</hi> 1378.</note> 
                  <hi>Rich.</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> did declare in an Act for that purpoſe, that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the 6th. and not his Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62184:20"/>
                  <hi>Clement,</hi> was duely choſen Pope, and ought to be accepted and obeyed in this Realm. I never ſaw the Original, but ſhall ſet down the Abridgment of it, out of Sir <hi>R. Cotton</hi>'s <hi>Exact Abridgment of the Records,</hi> in the following words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Act that Pope</hi> Urban <hi>was true and lawful Pope, and that the Livings of all Cardinals, and other Rebels to the ſaid Pope, ſhall be ſeized in the King's hands, and the King to be anſwered by the Profits thereof, and that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever within this Realm ſhall procure or obtain any Proviſion, or other Inſtrument, from any other Pope then the ſaid</hi> Urban, <hi>ſhall be out of the King's protection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Serjeant <hi>Raſtall</hi> hath another Abridgment of this Act, ſomewhat different in one paſſage, but in all the reſt to the ſame effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 2 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>It was agreed, that</hi> Urban <hi>was due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly elected Pope, and ought to be obey'd as Head of the Church, and that all Benefices and Poſſeſſions of Cardinals, and other the King's Enemies, ſhould be ſeized. And it was enacted,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſlal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,</hi> Tit. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion <hi>and</hi> Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire. p. <hi>356. 8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that if any purchaſed by proviſion, any Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſice or Grace, by any other named Pope then of Pope</hi> Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban, <hi>or be obedient to any other Perſon as Pope, he ſhould be out of the King's protection, and his Goods ſeized.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhould not have brought this Act upon the Stage, but that the Gentlemen of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, are ſo apt to miſcall our Church a <hi>Parliamentary</hi> Church, and our Religion a <hi>Parliamentary</hi> Religion, only becauſe our Laws confirm and eſtabliſh the Sanctions of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as the Imperial Laws and Edicts for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly did the Decrees of general Councils; particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as,<note n="*" place="margin">The exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Biſhop of the Church.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, who ſate in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, confirmed the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, and all other things that were ordained by the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> when he was but a <hi>Catechumenus,</hi> or Learner of the Chriſtian Religion. He ſaid of himſelf, that he was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>'E <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and after his death, the Fathers ſurnamed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62184:20"/>him, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>;<note place="margin">Equal to the Apoſtles.</note> and whoſoever will take the pains to run over, but with a curſory eye, the <hi>Novels</hi> of <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> the <hi>Nomocanons,</hi> and <hi>Baſilicks,</hi> the <hi>Capitularia</hi> of the old <hi>French,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Spelm. concil. vol. <hi>1</hi>
                  </note> and the Laws of our <hi>Ancient Saxon</hi> Kings, will find, that our religious Princes, ſince the Reformation, have intermedled no more with the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Church, then Chriſtian Princes formerly did.</p>
               <p>But to return thither, where I broke off, I deſire the Reader to take notice, That of 29 or<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Onuphrius</hi> reckons ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</note> 30 Schiſms in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I have taken notice but of nine, and that if it were requiſite to ſay more of the <hi>Roman</hi> Schiſms and Differences, I could add another Account of <hi>Anti Cardinals,</hi> and <hi>Anti-Councils,</hi> to this ſhort one of the <hi>Anti-Popes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Shewing, That Schiſms and Diviſions, and the conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, in oppoſite Communions, are no good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt the Truth, or Goodneſs, or Reputation of a Church.</head>
               <p n="2">II. HAving in the former Chapter, I hope, clearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, that the univerſal Church, and all the particular Members of it, are ſubject to <hi>Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Schiſms,</hi> I proceed in this to ſhew, that they are no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt the Trueneſs, or Goodneſs or Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any Church, becauſe what is incident to the whole Church, and all the parts of it, cannot be a good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt any <hi>one.</hi> If the Body may loſe an Arm, it can be no diſparagement to the Hand to have a Finger drop off; or if a Tree, to which St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> compares the Catholick Church, may have a Bough rent off from its Body, it can be no diſgrace to a Bough to loſe a rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62184:21"/>Branch, or to a Branch to loſe a rotten Twig. If the Hand cannot in reaſon or prudence upbraid the Foot with the loſs of a Toe, becauſe it may loſe a Finger, then certainly nothing ought to be concluded from a common Affection of all Churches, to the prejudice or diſhonour of this, or that particular Church.</p>
               <p>When our Saviour was told of the <hi>Galileans,</hi> whoſe bloud <hi>Pilate</hi> mingled with their Sacrifices, <hi>Suppoſe ye</hi> (ſaith he unto thoſe that told him of it) <hi>that theſe Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lileans were ſinners above all the Galileans, becauſe they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſuch things, I tell you nay, but except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh; or thoſe eighteen upon whom the Tower in Siloe fell, think ye that they were ſinners above all the men that dwelt in Jeruſalem, I tell you nay, but except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi> Our bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer teacheth us from theſe Examples, how unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and uncharitable it is to cenſure particular Perſons, when the common Misfortunes of Mankind fall upon them. For the <hi>Galileans,</hi> who were murdered by <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> at their Devotion, were no greater Sinners then other men; and thoſe upon whom the Tower in <hi>Siloe</hi> fell, were, it ſeems, as good as their Neighbour, tho' the <hi>Jews</hi> were ſo apt to think and ſpeak hardly of them for their Misfortune, contrary to the Doctrine of their own Scriptures, which taught them, that there is one Event unto all, and that no man can know the Love or Hatred of God by all that is before him. <hi>All things</hi> (ſaith the Preacher) <hi>come alike to all, there is one event to the righteous and to the wicked, to the clean and to the unclean, to him that ſacrificeth, and to him that ſacrificeth not.</hi> And as it is with particular men, in reference to the common Misfortunes of Mankind, ſo it is with par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches, in reference to Diviſions and Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are common Accidents to all Churches, good, or bad, true, or falſe, pure, or corrupt, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, or un-Catholick, that are called by the Name of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62184:21"/>Chriſt. They are all alike ſubject to Diviſions, and ſub Diviſions in Religion; and therefore thoſe who ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue againſt any Church upon that ſcore, treat her in the time of her Calamity, as <hi>Job</hi>'s Friends treated him, who turned his Misfortunes, which might have fallen upon themſelves, into Arguments againſt him, to prove that he was an Hypocrite, and not pure and upright, as he pretended to be.</p>
               <p>But in the primitive Times, men were not ſuch miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable comforters of Churches afflicted with Diviſions. Then they were better Logicians, and better Chriſtians, than to think a Church was not Catholick, or in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God, becauſe Hereſies and Schiſms aroſe in it; as appears from the Salutations which St. <hi>Paul</hi> gave unto the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> when it abounded with Hereſie, Faction, and Diſſentions, as I ſhewed in the former Chapter. In the beginning of both his Epiſtles, he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutes them in this manner: <hi>Paul, an Apoſtle of Jeſus Chriſt, unto the Church of God which is at Corinth.</hi> It was ſtill the Church of God, tho' there were Hereticks, and factious Parties of men in it; nay ſo far was he in his infallible judgement, from unchurching the Flock of Chriſt there upon the account of Diviſions, that he in effect apologized for them, and for the goodneſs and wiſdom of God that ſuffered them; for (ſaith he) <hi>there muſt be</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ac ſi diceret; ob hoc haereſeôn non ſtatim di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitùs eradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur authores, ut probati ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſti ſiant, id eſt, unuſquiſque quam tenax &amp; fidelis, &amp; fixus Catholicae fidei, ſit amator, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reat. <hi>Vincent. Lirin.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>hereſies among you, that thoſe who are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved may be made manifeſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So St. <hi>Clement</hi> begins his Epiſtle to the ſame Church, which was written upon the occaſion of a great Schiſm, in this manner, <hi>The Church of God at Rome, to the Church of God at Corinth.</hi> It ſeems the Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> rent and torn as it was with inteſtine Diviſions, was the Church of God as well as that of <hi>Rome,</hi> in which there were then no Diviſions at all. St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s next and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Succeſſor bewailed the ſad Misfortune of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> but he did not unchurch them for it; he
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62184:22"/>told them, how it occaſioned their venerable and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Name to be evil ſpoken of, but nevertheleſs he called them the<note n="*" place="margin">§. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>elect of God.</hi> And ſo <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, in an Epiſtle which he wrote to the <hi>Alexandrians,</hi> when they were very infamous, upon the account of the deadly Feuds and Separations which divided their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, ſalutes them in theſe words:<note n="†" place="margin">Socrat. <hi>H. E.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſtantine the Emperor, to the Catholick Church of Alexandria.</hi> Not long after, when the <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> conſpired againſt <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> to get the Emperor to depoſe him, and his Majeſty upon hearing his Cauſe, found their Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be falſe, he wrote a Letter in his behalf to the <hi>Alexandrians,</hi> of which this is the Title:<note n="*" place="margin">Athan <hi>opera, vol.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 779.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> the great Emperor, to the People of <hi>the Catholick Church,</hi> which is at <hi>Alexandria.</hi> When he wrote this Letter to the People of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> it abounded with <hi>Melitians</hi> and <hi>Arians,</hi> who had formed themſelves into oppoſite Communions, and yet thoſe ſchiſmatical oppoſite Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions, were in the judgement of that learned Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, no Argument againſt the <hi>Alexandrian</hi> Church. So <hi>Conſtantine</hi> junior, ſhortly after his Father's death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he aſſumed the Title of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> directed Letters to the Church of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> in favour of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> with this Superſcription:<note n="†" place="margin">Socrat. <hi>H. E. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſtantine Caeſar, to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Catholick Church of the Alexandrians.</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Sects and Sectaries of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> the Church ſtill remained Catholick, in the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Faithful, who retained the ancient Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Doctrine and Diſcipline. Theſe wiſe Emperors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that the Tares could not alter the property of the Wheat; and therefore tho' there were a World of Hereticks and Schiſmaticks in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and all the Regions round about it, yet they called the Church a Catholick Church. It was every jot as Catholick then, as it was before the <hi>Melitian</hi> and <hi>Arian</hi> Schiſms, when the People were of one mind, and one Communion; for
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62184:22"/>it is not the great number of Church members is any Dioceſs, Province, or Patriarchat, but the cauſe and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Communion, that makes a true Church. Otherwiſe, if Churches muſt be no longer reputed truly Catholick and good, then all the Members which are, or ought to be of it, are unanimous, and communicate together, then it muſt follow, that both the Church univerſal, and every particular Member of it, long ſince loſt their Catholick nature, and were no true Churches in the eyes of God. What, for inſtance, became of the Church Catholick, after the Council of <hi>Ariminum,</hi> when almoſt the whole Chriſtian World became <hi>Arian,</hi> except a very<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Libellus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, p.</hi> 8, 9, 10, 11. Vincent. Lirin. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> ſmall number of Biſhops, who ſtuck to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Catholick Faith? More particularly, what became of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when Pope <hi>Liberius</hi> embraced the <hi>Arian</hi> Communion, and ſubſcribed to the Sentence of the <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops againſt <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> as<note n="†" place="margin">Eccleſ. Ann. T. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>761, 762, 763.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Baronius</hi> acknowledges, tho' he endeavours to prove, that he never ſubſcribed to the <hi>Arian</hi> Confeſſion, or He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie? Nay what became of it, eſpecially upon their Principle, when Pope<note n="‖" place="margin">Vid. Nili Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcop. Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalon. de prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu Papae, lib. [qui eſt ad cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem Salmaſ. de primatu Papae,] p. <hi>33, 34, 35, &amp;</hi> p. <hi>61.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Honorius</hi> the 1ſt. fell into the Hereſie of the <hi>Monothelites,</hi> for which he was condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the 6th. General Council, and anathematized for it after his death by the 2d. Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> which they receive for the 7th. General Council? Nay, if Hereſies and Schiſms are good Arguments, or juſt matter of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception againſt any Church, what ſhall we ſay to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> upon the account of the <hi>Novatian,</hi> and all the other <hi>Antipapal</hi> Schiſms mentioned in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapter? Or to go farther back into Antiquity, what Apology ſhall we make for her, when<note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>H. E. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Blaſtus,</hi> and <hi>Florinus,</hi> a degraded <hi>Roman</hi> Presbyter, raiſed a great Schiſm in <hi>Rome,</hi> endeavouring to introduce new Doctrines, which<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Irenaeus</hi> confuted in Books written for that purpoſe? Their Doctrines were very abſurd, as well as inconſiſtent, with the Faith and Tradition of all
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62184:23"/>Churches, and yet they drew away many from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and enticed them to embrace their Opinions. Nay, what ſhall we do to defend her in the Time of Pope <hi>Victor</hi> and <hi>Zephyrinus,</hi> when ſhe was infeſted with the Hereſie,<note place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>H.E. l</hi> 5. <hi>c</hi> 28.</note> 
                  <hi>which aſſerted our Lord to be a meer man?</hi> This damnable Hereſie was firſt taught at <hi>Rome,</hi> by <hi>Theodotus,</hi> no better a man then a Tanner, for which he was excommunicated by Pope <hi>Victor;</hi> and afterwards in the Time of his Succeſſor <hi>Zephyrinus,</hi> it came to a perfect Schiſm, when the Hereticks made <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis</hi> the Confeſſor, a Biſhop of the Hereſie, and ſettled a Maintenance upon him. One of the Scholars of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus</hi> the <hi>Tanner,</hi> was another <hi>Theodotus</hi> a <hi>Banker,</hi> a great promoter of the Schiſm; and therefore I cannot but wonder, that any <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> who underſtands Antiquity, ſhould upbraid the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with the Preaching of Mechanicks and Tradeſmen, when a Tanner and a Banker, in the <hi>2d.</hi> Century, were the Ring-leaders of ſuch a peſtilent Hereſie in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and as an Author of that Time reports, <hi>impudently took upon them to adulterate the Scriptures, and reject the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the primitive Faith.</hi> Why ſhould men, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Senſe and Learning, uſe and Argument that is ſo eaſily retorted upon themſelves, and when it is purſued into all its Conſequences, makes it impoſſible for them to defend either the Church Univerſal, or any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Member thereof? What will they ſay for the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, by way of defence againſt the <hi>Gnoſtical</hi> Hereſies, if they argue againſt that, as they are wont to argue againſt the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Or to paſs over the Schiſms, of which I have given ſome Account in the former Chapter, how can they by their way of arguing, maintain the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> to have been Catholick, in the Time of <hi>Paulus Samoſatenſis,</hi> who revived the Hereſie of <hi>Theodotus,</hi> and taught, that <hi>Chriſt by nature was no more then a meer man?</hi> For this Reaſon, he held
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62184:23"/>Communion with the Followers of <hi>Artemon,</hi> the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this damnable Hereſie, teaching that Chriſt was from the Earth, and damning the Hymns which uſed to be ſung in Churches to his honour, as novel Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſures, and letting his Followers chant forth Hymns to his own praiſe in the Church, and tell the People that he was an Angel ſent from God. Was there ever ſuch an heretical and blaſphemous Archbiſhop in the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſince the Reformation, as this? But if there had been more then one ſuch, the Church of <hi>England</hi> nevertheleſs would have been a truly Catholick Church, as this of <hi>Antioch</hi> then was in the judgement of the Council that depoſed <hi>Paul.</hi> For in that excellent<note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb, <hi>H.E. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c</hi> 30.</note> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, which the Council wrote <hi>to the Biſhops and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters of the whole Catholick Church under Heaven,</hi> they tell them, after a long recital of <hi>Paul</hi>'s Impieties, that they were neceſſitated to depoſe him, and ordain ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his ſtead over <hi>the Catholick Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I might alſo ask them, upon their way of treating the Church of <hi>England,</hi> upon the ſcore of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies and Schiſms, what they can ſay for the Church of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in the Time of <hi>Macedonius</hi> and <hi>Neſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> who were both Patriarchs of that Church, and both fell into Hereſie and Schiſm? When a Biſhop and much more a Patriarch, leads the Flock into by-paths, the Schiſm is more deplorable, but yet it is not the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſie and Seceſſion of one, or two, or more Biſhops, if that ſhould happen, that can deſtroy the Catholick and Apoſtolick nature of any Provincial, Patriarchal, or National Church. For, as I obſerved before, it is not the number of Communicants, but the cauſe or ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Communion, that makes a true Church; and therefore were there both for kind and number, ten times as many more oppoſite Sects and Communions, as there are in this Nation, and Biſhops at the Heads of them all, yet upon ſuppoſition that the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:62184:24"/>is ſound and Apoſtolical in Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, that<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na eſt pars in quâ ſunt multi Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi, ſed ubi ſunt multi, illic—ſacra fides Chriſti violata eſt, ubi verò pauciſſimi ſunt, fides Chriſti vindicatur, Libell. precum, p 9, 12, 13.</note> ſmall number adhering to her Communion, muſt be the true Church. Nay if all the Biſhops of <hi>England,</hi> but one, ſhould fall away from the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that<note n="†" place="margin">Non dubitandum eſt paucos Epiſcopos eſle pretioſos merito conſeſſionis, &amp; inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis ſidei, multos vero nullifieri merito hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reseos—in causâ religiouis, &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crae fidei non numerus numero comparandus eſt, ſed pura illa Apoſtolica fides probata ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iliis, probata cruciatibus licet <hi>unlus,</hi> Multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum infidelitatibus praeponenda eſt. ibid.</note> one Biſhop, and the Flock adhering to him, would be the true Church of <hi>England,</hi> and as true and Catholick a Church, as if there were not one Diſſenter in the Land.</p>
               <p>The learned <hi>Papiſts,</hi> know this very well, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I wonder, that men pretending to Letters and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity, ſhould argue againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hereſies and Schiſms. Furthermore, if this be a good way of arguing againſt Churches, then the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> was twice involved in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of it; once by the Schiſm of <hi>Corah,</hi> and then by that of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who ſet up a Prieſthood and Altar a <hi>Bethel,</hi> in oppoſition to that of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and by the ſeparation out off ten Tribes in twelve from the true Church of God. Nay if this modiſh way of arguing be true, then the ſeparation of th Church of <hi>England,</hi> and other National Churches, from that of <hi>Rome,</hi> are as ſtrong Arguments againſt <hi>it,</hi> as the Sects and Schiſms among us are againſt the Church of <hi>England.</hi> There is no difference in the Caſe, becauſe they ſay, that all the Proteſtant Churches are ſchiſmatical for falling off from them, as we ſay the Congregational Churches are for falling off from ours; and if ours indeed is not a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, but apparently under God's diſpleaſure, becauſe forſooth they can tell us of the <hi>Presbyterians, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, Anabaptiſts,</hi> and <hi>Quakers,</hi> then we may by juſt conſequence ſay as much of theirs, becauſe we can tell them of the <hi>Waldenſes, Albigenſes, and Wiccliffians</hi> of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62184:24"/>old, and of late of the <hi>Lutherans, Calviniſts, and Church of England-men,</hi> who are all <hi>Separatiſts</hi> from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of <hi>Rome.</hi> As thoſe we repute Schiſmaticks, ſprang out of our Church and Communion, ſo thoſe whom they repute Schiſmaticks, ſprang out of theirs; and therefore would not any man wonder, that they ſhould ſo far forget themſelves, as to uſe ſuch Arguments againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and make ſuch Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon it, as may be eaſily retorted upon themſelves, to overthrow their own Pretenſions to Catholiciſm, and weaken the Cauſe, and Reputation of their Church.</p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (ſay they) is the Catholick Church, and the Church which Chriſt left upon Earth, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath ſeparated from it; and therefore, ſay we, in their looſe way of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing, the ſeparation of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is a good Argument againſt the Goodneſs and Reputation of that Church, which Chriſt left upon Earth. Nay, ſay they, <hi>Chriſt can have but one Church upon Earth, and we believe none can be that Church, but that which is called the Roman Catholick Church;</hi> but then, ſay we, a world of Hereſies and Schiſms have been bred in that one Church, the Catholick Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore it is long ſince this one Church of Chriſt was one, or a true, and good Church. <hi>Your Church</hi> (ſay the two late Converts to us) <hi>hath <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, or not? if not, then ſhe is not the Church of Chriſt; if ſhe hath, why are there ſo many Sects and Schiſms among you?</hi> Now, not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke ſuch Gentlemen <hi>to</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">A Net for the Fiſhers of Men, p. 111.</note> 
                  <hi>paint, and rip up the Sores of Proteſtancy,</hi> your Church (may a <hi>Turk</hi> ſay to them) hath Unity, or not? if not, then ſhe is not the Church of Chriſt; if ſhe hath, why are there ſo many Sects among you? You ſay, you are the one Catholick Church, but what ſhall we do to find it in ſuch and bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of Diſſenters as are in the Empire, <hi>France, Great Britain, Sweden, Denmark,</hi> and other Northern Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62184:25"/>and of<note n="*" place="margin">Ex to ordine <hi>[ſcilicet Cardinalium]</hi> ſunt quatuor, aut quinque, quorum nomina poſſum proferre, ſi vellem, quibus reverâ probetur noſtra doctrina, ſaltem magna ex parte, &amp; Romana exoſa ſit. Sed vae illis cum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Dei enunciaverit fore ut is qui nôrit voluntatem Domini &amp; non fec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>it vapulet pluribus, quam qui non noverit. Vae illis iterum, poeitentiam agant, nec ament glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam hominum magis quam gloriam Dei. <hi>P, Vergerius</hi> in Annot, in Catalogum Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticorum, <hi>p. 262.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Diſſemblers and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differents</hi> in <hi>Italy, Spain</hi> and <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> and even in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf. If a <hi>Mahumetan, Pagan,</hi> or <hi>Jew,</hi> ſhould argue thus againſt them, as they ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue againſt us, they muſt either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their own Conſequences, or ſink under the weight of them; nay, if an Atheiſt, or Infidel, of any other kind, ſhould take that advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage againſt Chriſtianity, from the Schiſms and Diviſions of it, which they do againſt the beſt Church of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I appeal to their own Conſciences, whether they muſt not deny their own Concluſions, or expoſe and betray the Cauſe of Chriſt. The Pagans argued ſo againſt Chriſtianity in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Times, becauſe ſo many Sects grew up with it, and therefore the variety of Hereſies and Schiſms, which have ſprung up in <hi>England</hi> ſince the Reformation, can be no Argument againſt the Church. It is no blemiſh to her to be in the ſame condition with the beſt and pureſt Churches, in the beſt and pureſt Times; it was ſo when the Apoſtles governed the Church, and the Spirit of God bid the Chriſtians, Try all things, and hold faſt that which is good.</p>
               <p>Hitherto I have proved, that <hi>Diviſions</hi> and <hi>Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> can be no good Argument, or matter of juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach againſt any Church, becauſe they are incident to all Churches, as I have ſhewed by a ſufficient Enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Particulars; and this will farther appear, if we conſider, that they may be Arguments for, as well as againſt a Church, and a cauſe of juſt praiſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of it, as well as of juſt reproach. When they are juſt and reaſonable, then indeed they are good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments againſt the Church where they ariſe, and give men juſt cauſe to reproach it; but when they are not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62184:25"/>juſt and reaſonable, but proceed from miſtake in thoſe that make them, or from worſe Cauſes, they they are good Arguments againſt the dividing Parties, and juſt matter of reproach to them, but none at all to the Church. Wherefore it argues want of Ingenuity, or great weakneſs of Judgement in men, to exclaim againſt a Church, upon the ſcore of Diviſions and Separations, before they have examined whether the Church or the Separatiſts are in the fault. In Reaſon and Charity this ought firſt to be done, before either the Church, or the Separators, or both, be condemned; but our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, without any regard to the Caſe betwixt the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the Diſſenters, loudly defame her in all Places with the Diſſentions and Separations, and object to our People the great difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and uncertainty of finding out, among ſo many oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Churches and Religions, which is the right, if there be any ſuch, and therefore exhort them to take Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in that Church, which is at unity in it ſelf, and looks ſo like the one Catholick Church. But God be praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the People of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are generally better inſtructed, then to be impoſed upon with ſuch looſe Talk. They underſtand very well, that as Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from corrupt and impure Churches is a neceſſary duty, ſo as long as there are Devils to tempt men, there will alſo be unjuſt Separations from found and Catholick Churches, and that therefore Separations and Diviſions in the general, can neither make for, or againſt any Church. They know very well, that Churches, like natural Bodies, are of different Tempers and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and that when any of them chances to undergo a ſeparation of Parts, the particular nature and conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it muſt be examined, before a man can ſafely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, whether the blamable Parts went off, or remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Church. In the ſeparation of Gold from the droſſie and ſpurious Parts; of Wine from the Lees;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62184:26"/>of Wheat from the Chaff; and of the excrementitious Parts from the Chyle and Bloud, the baſe and impure, and unprofitable Parts go off, and the good, and pure, and profitable, ſtay behind: but in the ſeparation of Wheat from Tares, of Flower from the Bran, and in all Chymical Separations, the good, the generous, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Parts go off, and the refuſe and feculent ſtay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind. I have made uſe of this familiar Compariſon, to ſhew how Separations and Diviſions in the general, can be no rational Argument for or againſt any Church, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it be known what king of Body that Church was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Separation; ſound or corrupt; pure or impure; Catholick or not Catholick; Apoſtolical or un. Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical: And when this is once ſtated, then it will appear, whether the Diviſions and Separations which were made from her, make for her or againſt her. I ſay, when it is firſt known what kind of Church a divided Church was, before the beginning of the Diviſion, then it may be known, whether the Diviſion objected againſt it, be an Argument for or againſt the Trueneſs, Soundneſs, and Purity of it; but to argue <hi>pro</hi> or <hi>con,</hi> from Separations, before this is ſtated, is but to talk at Random, which it doth not become men of Learning and Ingenuity to do. According to this Rule, the Divines of <hi>England</hi> firſt proved, that the Communion of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> was not pure and Apoſtolical, and thence juſtified the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Church of <hi>England</hi> from it as neceſſary; and on the contrary they have proved, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is pure and Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and thence condemn the Separation of the Diſſenters from it as needleſs. They argue <hi>à priori</hi> againſt both: on the one hand proving, that the Wheat went off from the Tares, and on the other, that the Chaff went off from the Wheat. But to argue <hi>à poſteriori,</hi> and in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral againſt a Church, meerly upon the ſcore of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, before we examine the Conſtitution of the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62184:26"/>Church, and ſtate the Caſe between her and the Dividers, doth become no men eſpecially no Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, but ſuch as having a weak Cauſe, muſt make uſe of popular, for want of found Arguments, and make the beſt they can of Sophiſtry, when Reaſon is not on their ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> That bare <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, or want of Schiſms and Diviſions in Religion, are no ſound Argument of the Truth, Goodneſs, or Reputation of a Church.</head>
               <p n="3">III. HAving ſhew'd in the ſecond Chapter, That Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and Separations are no Argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Trueneſs, or Reputation of any Church, I proceed to ſhew in this, That <hi>bare <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> or want of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, is no Argument for the Trueneſs, or Reputation of a Church; and this I ſhall endeavour to demonſtrate <hi>three ways:</hi> Firſt, By ſhewing, That it is not the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but the things in which a Church is united, that tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recommend and juſtifie a Church. Secondly, That Church-Unity may be the effect of culpable Cauſes, And thirdly, That all Churches, true or falſe, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick or not Catholick, are united in themſelves, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath more poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and actual Union in it, then that of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt then, It is not <hi>bare <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> but the things in which a Church is united, that muſt truly recommend and juſtifie it to the Chriſtian World, and prove it to be the Church of God. This is a ſelf-evident Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which all the Churches in the World will admit at firſt hearing, and the very Teſt, by which when Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes ariſe, they muſt be content to be tryed. For as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62184:27"/>to this Particular, it is juſt in Eccleſiaſtical, as it is in Civil Law and Government, where it is not the Union, but the Things or Cauſe in which men are united, that diſtinguiſh lawful from unlawful Societies and Meetings; otherwiſe if bare Union and Agreement, how ſtrict ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, were a Sign of, or a good Argument for the true and Catholick Church, then <hi>Aaron</hi> the high Prieſt, at the Head of that Congregation, which worſhipped the golden Calf, was the <hi>true Church</hi> of the <hi>Jews.</hi> He was their ſupream and lawful Paſtor, and they were very unanimous in making the Calf after his direction, and in building an Altar before it, and in oftering up Burnt-offerings and Peace-offerings, to uſe the new phraſe, <hi>in the preſence of it.</hi> They ſate down to eat and drink be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, and ſaid with one unanimous Acclamation, <hi>Theſe be thy Gods, O Iſrael, which brought thee out of the Land of Egypt.</hi> I believe there never was a more perfect Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Agreement in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> then among the Communicants of this ſinful Congregation, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs it was no Schiſm to divide from them, becauſe they united in a ſin. Their Union was their Crime, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the object of it was highly criminal, and God was provoked to conſume them, becauſe they agreed in a thing that was ſo abominable in his eyes.</p>
               <p>So the <hi>Corahites</hi> were as firmly united under <hi>Corah,</hi> as the true Church was under <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> Two hundred Princes of the Aſſembly, with a great number of People, were firmly united together in a Cauſe, wherein they ſtuck together to the death, even till the Earth opened her mouth, and ſwallowed them up, and they went down alive into Hell. So likewiſe the ten Tribes were as firmly united at <hi>Bethel,</hi> as the two were at <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> they had number as well as union to plead, but notwithſtanding both their number and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they were but a great Schiſm, becauſe they united in Innovations contrary to the will of God. So to paſs
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62184:27"/>from the Jews to the Chriſtians, there hath been at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times as ſtrict an Union among Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, as among the Catholicks. The <hi>Novatians</hi> in particular were remarkable for their Concord, Unity, and Unanimity. So were the <hi>Arians</hi> generally all of one Communion, and very unanimous againſt the <hi>Homouſian</hi> Doctrine, and yet they were but a great prevailing Schiſm when they were at the higheſt, and had almoſt gained the whole Chriſtian World.</p>
               <p>From theſe Examples it is plain, that in paſſing judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon Churches, we are not to look at the Union, ſo much as the Cauſe in which they are united. We are to conſider if their Doctrine and Diſcipline be <hi>Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> and their terms of Communion truly Catholick, and if they be ſo, then their Union in them is holy and laudable, and ſuch as makes them true Churches of God. A concurrence of theſe things, is the genuine badge of a<note n="*" place="margin">Ad bane it aque for mam probabuntur ab illis Eccleſiis quae licet nullum ex Apoſtolis, vet Apoſtolicis Autorem ſuum proſerant ut multò poſteriores, quae denique quotidie inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuuntur: <hi>tamen in câdem fide conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes, non minùs Apoſtolicae deputantur pro conſanguinitate doctrinae. Tertull.</hi> de praeſcript. Haereſ.</note> truly Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and Apoſtolical Church, and if thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, would have us admire their Union, and be made Converts by it, they muſt firſt make it appear to us that they are united in theſe things. Otherwiſe their Unity, inſtead of being an Argument for their Church, is a ſtrong Argument againſt it, to prove that it is but a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, and an over-grown Schiſm, from the one Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and Apoſtolical Church.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, Church-unity may be the effect of cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable Cauſes; and by culpable Cauſes, I mean, only ſuch as in a great meaſure make the embracing of any Religion, an <hi>inſpontaneous,</hi> or unwilling action: and theſe are only two, Ignorance and Compulſion, when men either are of a Religion, which they would not be of, if they knew the faults of it, or when knowing the faults of it, they would certainly forſake it, were they not under force, but left to their own free choice.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:62184:28"/>
               <p>Firſt then, <hi>Church-unity</hi> may be the effect of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, which was one great cauſe of the Unity and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of almoſt all Mankind in Paganiſm: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their <hi>ignorance of the Gentiles,</hi> is called <hi>darkneſs</hi> in the New Teſtament; as where our Lord is compared to the Day-ſpring, or Sun-riſing, which gave light to them that ſate in darkneſs, and in the ſhadow of death. So the Apoſtle of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> told them, It was their duty to ſhew forth the Praiſes of him, who had <hi>called them out of darkneſs</hi> into his marvellous light; and truly their ſpiritual darkneſs was ſo great, that God did in ſome meaſure excuſe their groſs error, in thinking that the Godhead could be like unto Gold, or Silver, or Stone, graven by Art, or man's device. Tho' men, who were worthy and abſurd Idaea's of him, yet, as the Apoſtle told the <hi>Athenians,</hi> The times of their former ignorance God winked at, but then commanded all the <hi>Gentiles</hi> every where at their utmoſt peril to repent.</p>
               <p>There never was a more ſtrict and general Union among the <hi>Jews,</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> then there was among the <hi>Greeks.</hi> For Paganiſm was become the Catholick Religion, or Superſtition, (as Catholick ſignifies univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal) and was ſpread far and wide upon the Earth; and yet, as the Apologetical Writers replied to the <hi>Greeks,</hi> when they argued from the extent of their Religion, and the conſent of Mankind in it, their great agreement in Idolatry was the effect of their Ignorance; as plainly appeared from the preaching of the Goſpel, upon which they forſook thoſe dumb Idols unto which they were carried, even as they were led, and turned from their former Vanities and Superſtition unto the living God. They worſhipped the Gods, and obſerved their impure Rites, becauſe they knew no better; but when their Underſtandings came to be well informed, then they made a new and manly choice, ſuch as proceeded from
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62184:28"/>all the Principles of humane Actions, and plainly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that Ignorance had hitherto been the Mother of their Idol-devotion, and by conſequence, that the choice of their former Religion wanted a ſufficient meaſure of knowledge, to make it a rational and truly willing choice.</p>
               <p>I wiſh thoſe who pride themſelves ſo much in the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> would conſider, how far the Sons and Daughters of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> may uſe this Plea in their own defence, againſt their ſo much celebrated Union. It is certain, that upon the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Writing of the Reformers, People came off in ſhoals from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in all Places where the Reformation was taught. Whole Kingdoms revolted as one man, to the aſtoniſhment of the Beholders on both ſides; and, I believe, no one man in the World, St. <hi>Paul</hi> excepted, ever made ſo many Proſelytes as <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> the <hi>Protevangeliſt</hi> of the Reformation in <hi>Germany,</hi> did; which is no ſmall preſumption, that their former adheſion to the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, was the effect of involuntary Ignorance, which is not conſiſtent with a truly free and rational choice. I am the more confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this opinion, when I conſider, that in Countreys, where there is the free exerciſe of both Religions, the number of Proſelytes from the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion to the Reformed, is daily much greater, then from the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Roman;</hi> particularly in <hi>France,</hi> notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the progreſſive Diſcouragements, which came like Wave after Wave upon the Proteſtants, for every Proſelyte Popery got from the Reformed Church, it perhaps gained ten from Popery, while it was lawful for it to receive Converts; and I appeal to the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the <hi>R. Cs.</hi> whether in all likelihood there would not ſoon be as many Proteſtants in <hi>Italy</hi> or <hi>Spain,</hi> as there were in <hi>France,</hi> if there were allowed the like meaſure of Knowledge and Liberty in thoſe Kingdoms,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62184:29"/>as there was in this. Let the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Italians</hi> have but the free uſe of the Scriptures, which is their Chriſtian Birth-right; give them but the Tranſlations which <hi>Cyprian de Valera</hi> made of the Bible in one Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and<note n="*" place="margin">He was Abbat of the Monaſtery of St. <hi>Michael de Lemo,</hi> of the Order of St. <hi>Benedict,</hi> and his Tranſlation of the Bible in <hi>Italian</hi> was Printed in the year 1477. when <hi>Sixtus Quartus</hi> was Pope.</note> 
                  <hi>Nicolaus de Malhermis,</hi> and<note n="†" place="margin">He tranſlated the New Teſtament from the Original into <hi>Italian,</hi> and it was Printed at <hi>Antwerp</hi> in 1538. and dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to St. <hi>Hercules Conzaga,</hi> Cardinal of <hi>Mantua,</hi> and the Dedication or Preface is almoſt nothing elſe but a Panegyrick of the Scriptures; but this and all his other Works were prohibited in that <hi>Index</hi> of prohibited Books, which <hi>P. P. Vergerius</hi> put forth with Annotations, and which was the firſt of that kind.</note> 
                  <hi>Antonio Brucioli,</hi> both their own men, made in the other, before the Reformation; and if upon the free uſe of theſe Bibles, and the Preaching of ſuch men as <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and <hi>Savanorola,</hi> and allowance to their Biſhops, to act according to the Powers of their Apoſtolical Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there do not ariſe a ſudden and mighty Epiſcopal Reformation in both thoſe Kingdoms, then I would acknowledge, that the Unity in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is perfectly Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical, and that the ſeceſſion of ours from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is an Apoſtaſie from the one Catholick Church.</p>
               <p>It is very well known, what<note n="‖" place="margin">Sleidan. <hi>Commentar. l.</hi> 15 <hi>in An.</hi> 1543.</note> 
                  <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Cohen, Duditius,</hi> Biſhop of Five Churches, and the two<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sleidan.</hi> Comment. l.<hi>21.</hi> in An. <hi>1548. Hiſt. Council of</hi> Trent, l. <hi>2.</hi> Meum etiam Germanum fratrem Baptiſtam Vergerium Polae Epiſcopum ob Paraphrafin in Pſalmum <hi>119.</hi> ſcriptum condemnant. <hi>P.P. Vergerius</hi> Annot. in Catal. Heret. p. <hi>263.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>119.</hi> ſeriptum condemnant. <hi>P. P. Vergerius</hi> Annot. in Catal. Heret. p. <hi>263. Vergerii,</hi> Brothers of immortal memory, not to mention other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, did in the Time of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; nay, Poſterity knows very well, how far the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Biſhops in the Council of<note n="†" place="margin">Hiſt, Council of <hi>Trent, l.</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Trent,</hi> maintained the divine Right of Epiſcopacy, in ſpight of the Legates, and that Biſhops derived their Authority immediately from Jeſus Chriſt, and not from the Pope. And no man that is acquainted with Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, can doubt, that if the Biſhops of the <hi>Roman</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion might maintain this Doctrine ſafely, they would maintain it freely and openly, and ſo wreſt the Keys out of the Pope's hand. They would, if they durſt, let his
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62184:29"/>Holineſs know, that they are his<note n="*" place="margin">Non eſt noſtri Romani Papae, non eſt tanta majeſtas ut terrere debeat: ficta eſt illa temporalis &amp; ſaſtuoſa majeſtas, uſurpata eſt, nulla eſt. Frater noſter ille eſt, Collega, &amp; Comminiſter. <hi>Antonius</hi> de Dominis in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilio Profectionis. <hi>§. 13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Fellows,</hi> and <hi>Collegues,</hi> and <hi>co-Boiſhops,</hi> as St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> called Pope <hi>Stephen;</hi> but they are quiet and peaceable, becauſe they are under Compulſion: By which I underſtand, ſuch a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty degree of penal Force and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, as ordinarily ſpeaking, will compel men to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with corrupt Churches, againſt the Dictates of their own Underſtandings; as extremity of ill Weather will conſtrain a Maſter of a Ship, with great reluctance, to caſt his <hi>Cargo</hi> over-Board, to ſave his own life, and the lives of his men. And when ſuch great Exigences force men to do any thing, which otherwiſe they would not do, they are ſaid to do it unwillingly, and to act againſt their Judgements, and Inclinations; and particularly, when for fear of <hi>ruining</hi> and <hi>exterminating</hi> Penalties, which, <hi>humanely ſpeaking,</hi> are intolerable, men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to any Religion, which otherwiſe they would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own; tho' as to outward Conformity, and Communion, they are of it, yet they are not for it in their hearts. I confeſs, me ought to endure any thing, rather then conform to any Religion, which they believe to be falſe, or ſubſcribe to any Confeſſion, which they believe not to be true; but yet we ſee the frailty of humane Nature is ſuch, that extream Severity will make them comply, againſt their wills, with a Religion they certainly know, and firmly believe to be falſe. Thus <hi>Plato,</hi> for fear of the Fate of his Maſter <hi>Socrates,</hi> continued in the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Polytheiſm, againſt the Dictates of his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. He knew there was but one true God, the Creator of all things, but he durſt not ſtand up for him, but, ſore againſt his will, frequented the Temples of the falſe Gods. So tho' <hi>Cicero</hi> knew the Vanity of the <hi>popular</hi> Gods, as he called them, in oppoſition to the one great God, yet he went to their Temples with the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62184:30"/>and ſaid, That their Anceſtors Religion was never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs to be had in Reverence, and retained, <hi>Reipubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae gratiâ</hi> that is in effect to ſay, A man ought not to diſſent from it, for fear he ſhould loſe his Skin. So the<note n="*" place="margin">Cum iram regis metuunt, cum non dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantur pro Chriſto filio Dei exilium perpeti — reſcindunt quod piè vindicaverant, &amp; ſuſcipiunt quod ut impium damnaverant. —Epiſcopi plus iram regis terreni ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muerunt, quàm Chriſtum verum Deum, &amp; ſempiternum regem.</note> Catholick Biſhops, in the Time of the <hi>Arian</hi> Controverſie, for fear condemned the Faith, againſt their own Conſciences, which they had publickly aſſerted before: Even good old<note n="†" place="margin">Sed &amp; ipſe Oſius accerſitus ad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantium regem, miniſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> perterritus, &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuens ne ſenex &amp; dives exilium pateretur, dat manus impietati, &amp; poſt tot annos prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varicatur in fidem. Libell precum.</note> 
                  <hi>Oſius,</hi> who had ſo long ſtood Champion for the Catholick Faith, fearing the Diſpleasure of the Emperor, did ſet his Hand to the <hi>Arian</hi> Confeſſion; and in the Reign of <hi>Valentinian,</hi> when the<note n="‖" place="margin">Socrat. <hi>H. E. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 15, 16, 17.</note> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks were ſo contumeliouſly uſed by the <hi>Arians,</hi> and were afflicted with moſt inſufferable Evils, they turned <hi>Arians</hi> apace, to avoid the violence of the Perſecution, tho' they ought to have endured it to the end. When Complaints ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified nothing, but to end in the ruine of the Complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the moſt eminent of the orthodox Clergy were burnt alive, for preſenting a Petition to the Emperor, then all the World almoſt became <hi>Arian</hi> on the ſudden, and was externally united in the <hi>Arian</hi> Faith. But as he is not a Jew which is one outwardly, neither is that Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion which is outward in the fleſh, ſo in this forced Conformity, all were not <hi>Arians</hi> that ſeemed to be <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> but many were ſo in external Communion, who hated <hi>Arianiſm</hi> in their hearts. And the like ſucceſs that the <hi>Arians</hi> had againſt the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> by methods of Severity, have ſome<note n="*" place="margin">Eò enim noſtris temporibus redactares eſt ut Eccleſiaſticae controverſiae, non Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis ampliùs, non Conciliis ſed tortoribus, ſed carnificibus ſed ſicariis, ſed ſanguinarris, ſed parricidis defendendae Romae, ant Româ com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittantur. <hi>Anton,</hi> de Dominis in Conſilio.</note> ſevere Popes and Princes had againſt thoſe, that have divided, or attempted to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which made Cardinal <hi>Soderinus</hi> tell <hi>Adrian</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:62184:30"/>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Hiſt Council <hi>Trent, l.</hi> 1.</note> the 6th. That the beſt way of rooting out Hereticks was by <hi>Cruſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and by exciting Princes and People to root them out; and to that end he bid him remember, that by theſe means <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> and his Succeſſors, happily ſubdued the <hi>Alhigenſes of Languedoc,</hi> the <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes Picards, poor men of Lyons, Arnoldiſts, Speroniſts, and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>vines;</hi> of whom there remained nothing but the very Names. And it ſhould ſeem that Pope<note n="‖" place="margin">P. P. Vergerius in Secret. Pont. Act. 2. Tamen ſcio cum Paulus III. anti paucos annos literas graviſſimas (Breve appellamus) ad Caeſarem &amp; Rom. Regem dediſſet in quibus erat ſcriptum, illos conſultiùs eſſe facturos, ſi bello contra Turcas omiſſo, bellum adorna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent contra Lutheranos, quippe qui eſſent Turcis ipſis lange pernicioſiores, &amp; deterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> was of that Cardinal's opinion, who in a Brief to the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the 5th. and his Brother <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> tells them, That it were more adviſedly done, if they would clap up a Peace with the <hi>Turks,</hi> and bend all their Force againſt the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans,</hi> who were far worſe, and more pernicious than the very <hi>Turks.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. Council <hi>Trent. l.</hi> 5.</note> So <hi>Paul</hi> the 4th. importuned the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> to ſettle the Inquiſition in their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, as the only means to extirpate Hereſies; and at his Death, he recommended nothing to the Cardinals, but the Office of the holy Inquiſition, which, he ſaid, was the only Expedient to preſerve the Church, exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to employ all their Endeavours to get it eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in <hi>Italy,</hi> and whereſoever elſe they could. He uſed to ſay, It was the <hi>principal Secret, and Myſtery of the Papacy;</hi> but whether it were ſo or no, it cannot be denied, but that the Union of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is in a great meaſure beholding to it, where it is moſt entire.<note n="†" place="margin">Id. l. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> After the Death of that Pope, <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> rooted out <hi>Lutheraniſm,</hi> which had taken happy Root in that Kingdom, by extream Severity. He no ſooner arrived from <hi>Flanders</hi> at <hi>Sevill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. l. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> on the 24th. day of <hi>September,</hi> 1559. but he cauſed <hi>Johannes Pontius,</hi> Count of <hi>Bayleno,</hi> with a Preacher, and ſome others of the Colledge of St. <hi>Iſidore,</hi> where the Religion was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62184:31"/>together, with ſome Ladies of Quality, in all 13 Perſons, to be burnt for <hi>Lutherans;</hi> as alſo the Statue of <hi>Conſtantinus Pontius,</hi> Confeſſor to his Father <hi>Charles,</hi> who ſerved him in his Retirement, and held him in his Arms when he expired. Afterwards, at <hi>Valladolid,</hi> he cauſed 28 of the prime Nobility of the Countrey to be burned in his preſence. The <hi>Spaniards,</hi> eſpecially the Nobility, had at that time a great averſion to the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> but this extream Severity of <hi>Philip</hi> made them conceal their inward Reſentments, and every one, who knows that piece of Hiſtory, muſt confeſs, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is obliged for its Unity in <hi>Spain</hi> to the memory of that Prince, and the continuance of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition from his Time till now. The Hereſie, as 'tis miſ-called, was rooted out of the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi> by the deſtruction of 50000 Perſons: And we know by what Methods it hath been ſince extirpated in other Places, where thouſands of Souls, who would have counted Death a mercy, have been brought to ſubſcribe a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, contrary to their former Religion which they ſtill believe in their hearts. P. P. <hi>Vergerius</hi> ſaith, That in that Age, (the Age of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation<note n="*">Quantus eſt numerus noſtrâ aetate non mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orum, qui mortis, carcerum, atque tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remium, ſed etiam qui exitiorum tulerunt, &amp; ſerunt etiamnum martyria? Qui jam mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grârunt ad dominum deum noſtrum per ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra, inquam, martyria, ſunt fermè <hi>millia centum.</hi>—Cum his vero conjunguntur voces circiter 15000 exulum, qui deſertâ patriâ, deſertis parentibus, deſertis amicis, atque bonis alibi vivunt. P. P. Vergerius Annot, in Catalog. Haeret.</note>,) almoſt 100000 Souls had been put to death, for refuſing Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, beſides thoſe that were, condemned to Priſons, Gallies, and Baniſhment. And theſe Inſtances are enough, without any more, to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, That the Unity of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, is in great part the effect of Force and Compulſion, which much diminiſhes the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of it, and might prevail with our Neighbours of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, if they conſidered it aright, not to admire it, and talk of it ſo much, and ring us in the Ears with it in all Places, as if it came not at all from
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62184:31"/>Violence, but altogether by Inſpiration from the Spirit of God.</p>
               <p>But in the laſt place, Bare Unity, or want of Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is ſo far from being an Argument for the Trueneſs, or Honour of any Church, that it is a common Affection which belongs to all Churches, true or falſe, good or bad, Catholick or un-Catholick, ſmall or great, as they are Societies of men; and beſides, the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hath more Union, both potential and actual in it, then the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> To prove the firſt Part of this Aſſertion, we need but remember, That it is Union and Agreement under certain Laws and Rules of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which makes all Societies among Men and Angels, and wicked Societies are many times as well formed, and as firmly united, as the pure, the holy, and the good. <hi>Lucifer</hi> and his angels are a Guild, or Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Spirits, as well as <hi>Michael</hi> and his, and are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a political oeconomy of the ſame nature; and he that underſtood it very well, ſaid, That Satan was not divided againſt Satan, becauſe if he were, his kingdom could not ſtand. But it hath ſtood firm and undivided, ever ſince it was firſt formed, before the ſenſible Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it was never yet ſhaken with inteſtine Diviſions, there was never two or three oppoſite Soveraigns at one time in that curſed Hierarchy, nor two or three Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to the Chair of <hi>Lucifer:</hi> And therefore, I hope, bare Unity, or want of Diviſions, will never hereafter paſs among conſidering men, for a mark of a truly Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church. And as it is among Spirits, ſo 'tis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men: The worſt Fraternities have ſometimes the firmeſt Union; as we of this Nation very well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Time, when thoſe of the great Rebellion boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that God had united the Hearts of his People in his Cauſe as one Man; nevertheleſs thoſe pretended People of God, whoſe Hearts and Hands were ſo united, that we could not break their Bonds of Union aſunder, were
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62184:32"/>no better then a Band of Rebels, and their Cauſe down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Rebellion againſt God, and the beſt of Princes, tho' they acted in it as if they had been all informed with one common Soul. The like hath often happened in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Societies: The <hi>Samaritans,</hi> who had neither <hi>Sadduces,</hi> nor <hi>Phariſees,</hi> nor <hi>Eſſenes,</hi> nor <hi>Herodians,</hi> nor <hi>Cabaliſts,</hi> nor <hi>Carraites,</hi> among them, for that Reaſon had a firmer Union among themſelves, then the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> had, and yet they were not the true Church. So among the ancient Chriſtians, the <hi>Novatians</hi> lived in perfect Peace and Unity among themſelves, when there were many Feuds and Contentions among the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks: Which ſhews, that bare Unity is not a good <hi>Teſt</hi> whereby to try Churches; or if it were, I am confident, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> upon a fair tryal, would carry the Garland from the <hi>Roman,</hi> and appear to be the more Catholick Church.</p>
               <p>Could there be found any fit and indifferent Judge between them, I durſt, as far as I am concerned, put the merit of the Controverſie between us and the <hi>R. Cs.</hi> upon this ſingle point of Union, and would engage to render my ſelf a Proſelyte, if their Church carried the Cauſe. Perhaps they may think his a very bold Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, becauſe of the great number of Sectaries that have gone out from us; but then they are to conſider, that as the Proteſtants, which in ſeveral Parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeveral Denominations, have gone out from them, are now nothing unto them, ſo neither are the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational Sects, which went off from us, any thing, or of any account to us: But take our Church, and theirs, as they are preciſely in themſelves, without any regard to their reſpective Separations, and I am very confident, for all their boaſtings of Union, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> will be found to have both more potential and actual Union in it, then the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> For firſt, as to potential Union, however the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62184:32"/>actually united, it hath the ſeeds of Diviſion in its Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els; and as <hi>Rebeckah</hi> once had different Nations, ſo has ſhe different Churches ſtruggling in her Womb. The Principle of the Pope's Supremacy, is it ſelf ſufficient, were there no more, to cauſe continual Feuds and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in the Popedom; and<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>In his excellent Tracts,</hi> De cauſis diſſentionum in Eccleſiis, &amp; de primatu Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pae ad calcem Salmaſii de primatu Papae.</note> 
                  <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> did moſt judiciouſly aſſign it, for the cauſe of all the Diviſions that then tore the Catholick Church into pieces, the Biſhops of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom not being able to endure the Uſurpation, nor other Churches, contrary to their fundamental Liberty, to be Subjects to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. The exerciſe of this uſurped Power of the Pope's, being the ſupream ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Univerſal Church, is that, which makes the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops themſelves ſigh and murmur in private, and ſay with <hi>Spalatenſis,</hi> where they can ſay it ſafely, <hi>Frater noſter ille eſt, Collega, &amp; Coepiſcopus nobiſcum;</hi> and however they conceal their Reſentments, as the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Prelates did before the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> yet they are willing, upon the firſt opportunity, to aſſert their Apoſtolical Equality, and like the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prelates, at the time of the Reformation, will be glad when they can do it with a proſpect of ſucceſs, to caſt off the Yoke, which makes Chriſtendom groan, and which neither they nor their Predeceſſor were able to bear. Let but Chriſtian Princes ſay the word, and then we ſhall ſee what the Biſhops will do; or let there be but a free and general Council indeed, and then let us ſee if the Pope ſhall not be told in both ears, That the Church Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal is a great Colledge, and the Government of it Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratical; that the Epiſcopat is one, but that it is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded among all Biſhops, whereof every one hath his ſhare; that the Apoſtles received equal Power and Authority from the ſame Maſters; that the Biſhops were their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, and that the other Biſhops receive their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62184:33"/>no more from the Succeſſor of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> then he doth from them, but that all receive it alike from <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> When it ſhall be ſafe, the Biſhops of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church will talk and write as much to this purpoſe, as ever the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Divines did, who in aſſerting this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, follow the Example of their Anceſtors before the Reformation; I mean, the <hi>Saxon</hi> Biſhops, one of whom in his Advice to his Clergy, ſpeaks thus:<note n="*" place="margin">Ge sceolon eac ƿitan þat eoƿre hades syndan þa aesteran hadar aester urum hadum. and us þa nystan. gelice þa biscopas syndan ongeƿrixle þara Apos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tola on þaere haligþa gesom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunge. sƿa syndan þa maesse pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ostas on þam geprixle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pister þegna. þa B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>opas Aapones. and þa maesse preostas ƿone had his suna. <hi>Spelm. Concil. uol.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 586.</note> 
                  <hi>Ye ought to know, that your Order is next after, and next to ours; for as the Biſhops are in the place and ſtead of the Apoſtles, over the holy Church, ſo are the Prieſts in the place of the Diſciples. The Biſhops are of the Order of Aaron, and the Prieſts have the Order of his Sons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Doctrine, in all likelihood, will one day revive againſt the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Pontif; for the Spirit of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata</hi> will for ever be upon the learned Prelates, who like Elaſtick Bodies under preſſure, are under a conſtant inclination to recover their liberty, and will recover it, as ſoon as they can.</p>
               <p>The next dividing Principle in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is, The Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, which is a Doctrine more full of Contradictions, then perhaps any other, which Men or Angles can invent. It is contrary to all the Senſes and Reaſon of Man; to the plain and obvious ſenſe of thoſe very words upon which it is grounded; to the Belief of the ancient Catholick Church; to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of almoſt all Sciences: It multiplies the hypoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Union; it makes Chriſt to have offered up himſelf a propitiatory sacrifice, before he was offered upon the Croſs: In a word, the Contradictions involved in it, are almoſt innumerable, by which it equally choaks the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62184:33"/>learned and unlearned; and as it hath made, ſo it will for ever make Diſſenters in great abundance, and no man, nor any Church, can ever want a juſt pretence of dividing from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as long as it is an Article of her Faith. Theſe two Principles, without naming any more, naturally tend to making of Diviſions after Diviſions among them, notwithſtanding all the actual Union of which they boaſt. But the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath no ſuch dividing Principles, theoretical or practical, in her Conſtitution; nothing is required to Communion with her, but what is primitive and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical, and how much ſoever ſhe hath been, or is broken, and divided, yet her Communion is truly Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, and tends to Peace and Coaleſcence, and even now her Wounds are cloſing apace, and ready to heal of themſelves.</p>
               <p>And as the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath more potential Union in her, then that of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo hath ſhe more actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Union too; for her Clergy and People have no ſuch fierce and bitter Contentions among them, as there are betwixt the <hi>Iriſh Remonſtrants</hi> and <hi>Anti-Remonſtrants,</hi> the <hi>Moliniſts</hi> and <hi>Janſeniſts,</hi> as well as <hi>Thomiſts,</hi> and <hi>Scotiſts,</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> ſome of which oppoſite Parties will not communicate with one another. And as for the Difference among them, concerning the Judge of Controverſies, and whether the Pope be ſubject or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to a general Council, it tends naturally, and by due rational conſequence, to the diſſolution of their Communion; and who knows but we may live to ſee the Comedy of <hi>Baſil</hi> acted over again, and one part of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church declaring for a general Council, and the other for the Pope.</p>
               <p>Nay I may ſay, that at this preſent the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have been, and are united, to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration and Envy, and better then the Clergy often happened to be in the ancient Catholick Church. Had
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62184:34"/>our Biſhops ever ſuch Broils among them, as happened betwixt the Biſhops of the Eaſtern and Weſtern Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, about no greater a Matter, then the keeping of <hi>Eaſter?</hi> And between <hi>Cpyrian,</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> and <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian,</hi> three Metropolitans, and their Adherents on the on ſide, and the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and his, on the other, about re-Baptization, when they made no bones of<note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliani contra Ep. Stephani in cyprian. edit. Rigalt. p. <hi>143.</hi>
                  </note> taxing the Pope with Inhumanity, Inſolence and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? Or had we ever reaſon to take up that Complaint againſt them, which<note n="†" place="margin">H. E. l. <hi>3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> made againſt the Biſhops of the Catholick Church, before the <hi>Diocleſian</hi> Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That they were, as it were, at War among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and wounded one another with words, as with Darts and Spears, nay, that they daſhed and ſplit like capital Veſſels one upon another, ſtriving for prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, and enlarging the bounds of their Dioceſſes, which cauſes great Factions among the People? Or, to deſcend to more particular Inſtances, Was there ever ſuch a tragical Quarrel between any of our Archbiſhops, or Biſhops, ſince the Reformation, as happened between <hi>Theophilus,</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and <hi>John Chryſoſtom,</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople? Epiphanius,</hi> who ſided with <hi>Theophilus,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">Socrat. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>.14.</hi>
                  </note> curſed one another,<note n="*" place="margin">Socrat. l. <hi>16.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> much Bloud was s;hed on both ſides, and the Cathedral Church of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> with the Senate-houſe, were burnt in the Quarrel down to the ground.<note place="margin">Sozom. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Sozomen</hi> proteſts, he was aſhamed to tell many things which happened in this Quarrel, leſt Infidels ſhould come to the knowledge of them; and ſaith<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>An.</hi> 400. <hi>n.</hi> 31.</note> 
                  <hi>Baronius,</hi> going to tell the Story of it: I ſhall now deſcribe a curſed Perſecution, not of Pagans againſt Chriſtians, or of Hereticks againſt Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, or of wicked againſt good men, but, what is mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous and prodigious, of Saints and holy men, one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another.</p>
               <p>to proceed, Did the Biſhops of <hi>England,</hi> ſince the Reformation, ever accuſe one another in written Libels
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62184:34"/>before the King, as the<note n="ſtar;" place="margin">Sozom. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> Biſhop in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council did before the Emperor? Or is there now any occaſion of uſing againſt them the words, which<note n="†" place="margin">Vit. Nazianz. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ixa operibus Nazianz. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>è <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>tis Pariſ. <hi>1630.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpoke in a Council of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which went about to depoſe him: <hi>It is a ſhame, my fellow-Paſtors of Chriſt's Flock, and not befitting you, to fall to war among your ſelves, while you are to teach others peace, and perſwade them to live in unity.</hi> To conclude, How many ſuch ſharp Contentions have happened among our Biſhops, as we read happened between <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas, Acts</hi> 15. 39. and between <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter, Gal.</hi> 2.11. where we read, that becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> was to be blamed, he withſtood him to his very face. Had the Clergy, and People of our Communion, been long or often exerciſed by ſuch Broils as theſe, the <hi>R. Cs.</hi> would have had a fair pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to reproach us with want of Unity; but the God of Union be praiſed for it, we have no ſuch Feuds and Contentions among us, but quite contrary, are as faſt cemented among our ſelves in Love and Union, as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve any Church of the like extent ever was in the World.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> An Enquiry into the True Cauſes of Schiſms and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions.</head>
               <p>HAving ſhewed from ſeveral Arguments in the foregoing Chapter, That <hi>bare <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> or want of Diviſions, is no Argument for the Trueneſs or Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a Church, I ſhall, for the farther advantage of my Plea, proceed in this, to make enquiry into the Cauſes of Diviſions and Schiſms, and more particularly, into the Cauſes of theſe in <hi>England,</hi> with which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians <hi>Roman</hi> Communion are pleaſed ſo to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid our Church.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:62184:35"/>
               <p>Now in this enquiry into the Cauſes of Diviſions and Schiſms, I ſhould very much forget both the ancient Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh and Chriſtian Theology, if I did not in the firſt place name the <hi>Devil,</hi> by whom we are not to underſtand any ſingle evil Spirit, but the whole ſociety of apoſtate Angels, who are moſt malicious and implacable Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of God, and of Man for God's ſake, and of the Church, above all other Societies of Men. This Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine we have not only from the Scriptures of the Old and New. Teſtament, but from the moſt ancient primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtian Writers, who, as it were, with one voice, aſcribe unto the Devil, Idolatry, Perſecution, Hereſie and Schiſm. He is meant by the Enemy in our Saviour's Parable, who took his opportunity while men ſlept, to ſowe Tares in the Field of the Church: And according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who was not ignorant of his devices, calls Hereſies the doctrines of Devils, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. ſaith he, The Spirit ſpeaketh expreſly, that in the latter days ſome ſhall depart from the truth, giving heed to ſeducing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and doctrines of Devils: And in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12. ſaith he, Put on the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to ſtand againſt the wiles of the Devil, for we wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle not againſt fleſh and bloud, but againſt principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and powers, againſt the rulers of the darkneſs of this world, againſt ſpiritual wickedneſſes, or wicked ſpirits in high places. All theſe are ſeveral expreſſions for that ſociety of apoſtate Spirits, which make up the kingdom of darkneſs; as is plain from the 1 ſt. and 2d. Verſes of the 11 th. Chapter of the ſame Epiſtle, where he ſaith, <hi>Ye were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, wherein you walked according to the courſe of this world, according to the prince of the power of the air, the ſpirit that now work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the children of diſobedience,</hi> who cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to believe the Goſpel. Wherefore the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, for which Chriſtians are to fortifie themſelves, are not only againſt humane Enemies, but the powers of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62184:35"/>darkneſs, the whole ſociety of Devils, who were the Gods of the <hi>Gentile</hi> World. They are always plotting and contriving, againſt the Church, and when they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hurt it with Idolatry, Polytheiſm, or Perſecutions, then they ſtrive to get Altar ſet up againſt Altar in it, and diſtract it with Hereſie and Schiſm. Accordingly St. <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> in his Ep. to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> calls Hereſies and falſe Doctrines, Herbs, or Plants of the Devil's planting; and tells them in the ſame Epiſtle, That to meet often toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and receive the holy Euchariſt in peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, was the only way to weaken the powers of Satan, and prevent the ruine and deſtruction he would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe bring upon them by Diviſion; and to convince them how malicious and vigilant an enemy he is to the Church, he tells them, That there were three Myſteries of the Chriſtian Religion which were kept from his knowledge, <hi>The Virginity of Mary, her bringing forth, (or the Nativity of her Son) and the Death of our Lord.</hi> Had Satan come to the knowledge of theſe Myſteries, unleſs God had chained him and his evil angels up, they would have made ill uſe of them againſt the great deſign of man's Redemption; and accordingly many learned men have given his for one Reaſon of the obſcurity of the Prophecies, and why God was pleaſed ſo artificially to conceal many things in them, leſt Satan coming to the knowledge of them, ſhould endeavour to prevent or obſtruct the fulfilling of them, or enervate the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty and demonſtration of them, after they were ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. Thus <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in his firſt, commonly called the ſecond Apology, obſerves, That he did before-hand to the beſt of his skill, teach and inſtitute many things among the Pagans, which had ſome ſemblance with the future Myſteries of the Chriſtian Religion, that ſo when they came to paſs, they might not ſeem ſuch divine and wonderful Myſteries, as indeed they are. The like is obſerved by<note n="*" place="margin">Tert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ſcript. Haeres, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>40.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> after him, and made out by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62184:36"/>particular Inſtances, to which I remit the curious Reader, which ſhews, That he hath a great and active ſpite againſt the Church of God, more eſpecially againſt ſuch parts of it as are pure in Doctrine or Worſhip, to ſow Hereſies and Schiſms among them and divide the unity of their Communion: And therefore the ſame St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> in his Ep. to the <hi>Tralleſians,</hi> bids them beware of Separations and Diviſions, as of the Snares of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; and in his Ep. to the <hi>Philadelphians,</hi> he prays them in his wonted phraſe, to abſtain from the evil Herbs, which Chriſt never cultivated, becauſe they were not of his heavenly Father's planting, meaning the Weeds of falſe Doctrines, which Satan had ſowed among them, and which, he ſaith, did not only cauſe different Parties among them, but a perfect ſeparation of many from the Church. So <hi>Juſtin</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">P. 403.</note> 
                  <hi>Martyr</hi> in his Dialogue with <hi>Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho,</hi> aſcribes all the impious and blaſphemous Doctrines, which were then taught in the Name of Chriſt, to the Inſpirations of the unclean ſpirit of the Devil; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly when St. <hi>Polycarp</hi> met <hi>Marcion</hi> the Heretick, he told him, He knew him to be the eldeſt Son of the Devil, as being a man who was acted with diabolical Impulſe and Inſpirations; and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in the Book above-cited, ſaith expreſly, That the Devil is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Hereſie as well as Idolatry. The like is obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Theodoret,</hi> who aſcribe all Hereſies to the invention and artifice of the Devil; and all the Hiſtories of Hereſies and Schiſms in Eccleſiaſtical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, are ſtill uſhered in with prefatory Complaints of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the envious and wicked Devil, whoſe buſineſs hath been from the beginning to deceive, and moleſt the Church of God. Nay, the purer any Church is in Doctrine and Worſhip, the more, we may be ſure, he will ſtickle againſt it, and endeavour to weaken and diſgrace it by inteſtine Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and perſwade the dividing Parties to form them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into oppoſite Schiſms.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:62184:36"/>
               <p>Indeed where Churches are already corrupted in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Worſhip, and firmly adhere to thoſe Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, 'tis his intereſt to let them alone, and not to hazard the Reformation of them, by ſtirring up Contentions and Diviſions in them; but in Churches, where the Doctrine and Worſhip are kept pure and Apoſtolical, by the care and vigilance of the Paſtors; in Churches, where the Scriptures are openly taught and read, and the whole Worſhip of God, but more eſpecially the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are duly adminiſtred by lawful Miniſters, and the Communion of Saints carefully maintained: In ſuch pure and Apoſtolical Churches as theſe, he hath no other game to play, but to get them, as far as he can, extirpated by Perſecutions; or where that fails, to make Mutinies, and Diviſions, and Schiſms in them, and ſo to weaken the common Intereſt of the whole, by dividing it into parts. Where he cannot unite the Members of a Church in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Doctrines and Practices, he will labour hard to diſſolve them by pernicious Schiſms; where he cannot unite them againſt Truth, he will ſtrive to divide them againſt Charity; and where they will not agree, he will make them, if he can, differ to their own deſtruction: And therefore conſidering him as the principal Cauſe of Diviſions, all that can be concluded, upon that Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, againſt any particular Church, is only this, That the Members of it are ſubject, like the Members of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches, to be deceived and drawn away by the Devil; and if upon ſpecial enquiry, it be found, that ſhe is pure and Apoſtolical in her Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, all that can then be concluded, is no more then this, That the Devil is become her particular Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and hath a particular ſpite againſt her, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of her Excellence and Worth. This is the worſt Conſequence that can be drawn from Diviſions and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, againſt ſuch a Church as ours, and we are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to admit it, we are willing to acknowledge, that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:62184:37"/>the Devil hates the Church of <hi>England</hi> more then many Churches, and, if thoſe that object our Diviſions to us pleaſe, very much more then the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> We are willing to look upon the many Hereſies and Schiſms among us, as the effects of his Revenge againſt her, for the damage he hath ſuſtained by her; as<note n="*" place="margin">Videns ille idola derelicta &amp; per ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miùm credentium populum ſedes ſuas as tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla deſerta, excogitaverit novam fraudem, ut ſub ipſo Chriſtiani nominis titulo fallat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cautos: hereſes invenit &amp; ſchiſmata, quibus ſubverteret ſidem, veritatem corrumperet, ſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret unitatem. <hi>Cyprian</hi> de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit Eccleſ.</note> St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> thought the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Schiſms of his Time, were purpoſely invented by him, to be revenged of the Chriſtian Religion, for deſtroying his Worſhip among the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> All this we are willing to admit upon the Theory that ariſeth, from conſidering the firſt Cauſe of Diviſions and Separations, and let thoſe who love to reproach the Church of <hi>England</hi> with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Diviſions Religion, make the beſt of it they can.</p>
               <p>But then to proceed farther in this Enquiry: After we have found out the principal, we muſt look after the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental Cauſes of Diviſions and Separations, and they, according to the Ancients, who ſpoke what they knew to be true by long Experience and Obſervation, were <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, over-curious, ambitious, covetous,</hi> and <hi>contentious men.</hi> Theſe are the proper Inſtruments by which the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil acts, in broaching falſe Doctrines, and making Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Separations. He is a ſagacious Spirit, and can find out the weak and blind ſide of every man, where he will be ſure to ply him with Darts of Temptation, as a skilful General will be ſure to attack the weakeſt part of the Wall, or that part of it which is leaſt defended, when he ſtorms a Town.</p>
               <p>The firſt Inſtrument then by which Satan works, in making Schiſms and Diviſions, are ignorant men, or men ignorant in the Scriptures, whoſe Ignorance makes them confident, and think they underſtand the Scriptures, when for want of knowing the received ſence of them,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62184:37"/>they do not. This St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> complains of in one of his Sermons:<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hom.</hi> 37 <hi>T.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 245.</note> Saith he, The ignorance of the Scriptures is a dangerous Precipice, and a deep Gulf of deſtruction, and a great betrayer of mens Salvation. It is that which hath brought forth Hereſies, and which turns all things upſide down. So in his<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>T.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 1.</note> Preface to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Ep. to the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſaith he, A thouſand Evils come from ignorance of the Scriptures, and the manifold ſorts of Hereſies have ſprung from thence. To this purpoſe ſpeaks a more anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Author in Anſwer to this Query, <hi>Why God, if he was able to do it, did not root out all Errors and Hereſies.</hi>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">Author. reſponſ. ad Orthodoxos in resp. ad <hi>1.</hi> Quaeſt.</note> Saith he, When God abrogated Judaiſm, he introduced the New inſtead of the Old Teſtament, and if all thoſe who embrace Chriſtianity, do not agree in thier Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but ſome believe right, and ſome otherwiſe, this is not the fault of God, nor to be aſcribed to any defect of care, or power in him, but the fault of their own careleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and negligence, nor ought any man to be offended at the ſmall number of orthodox Chriſtians, becauſe it is written, That many are called, but few choſen; and that ſtreight and narrow is the way which leadeth unto life, and few there be that find it. It is obſervable, that theſe ancient Fathers did not lay the blame of Hereſies and Schiſms, upon the free and common uſe of the Scriptures, but upon the careleſs and negligent reading of them, and to ignorant mens preſuming they underſtood them, when they did not: The fault was not in the Scriptures, but in thoſe who through ignorance abuſed them; the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were always common in all Churches and Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and I dare ſay boldly, ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">De praeſcript. Heret. § <hi>39.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian, That the Scriptures are ſo contrived by the will of God, that they ſhould afford occaſion for Hereſies, becauſe I read that there muſt be Hereſies, and Hereſies cannot be without the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> What I have obſerved out of theſe ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is no more in effect then what St. <hi>Peter</hi> obſerved of the Epiſtles of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which are one great part of the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62184:38"/>Scriptures. Saith he, <hi>Account that the long-ſuffering of the Lord is ſalvation, even as our beloved Paul alſo according to the wiſdom given unto him, hath written unto you, as alſo in all his Epiſtles ſpeaking in them of theſe things, in which are ſome things hard to be underſtood, which they that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned and unſtable wreſt, as they do alſo the other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, unto their own deſtruction.</hi> The Scriptures, it ſeems, ſuffered very much by unlearned men in the Time of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and yet he did not order them to be kept from the People, neither in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor any other Churches. He knew that they were holy, true, juſt, and good, and were deſigned by God for publick uſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, and if ignorant men, by the inſtigation of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and their own natural Enthuſiaſm, did miſuſe them, and draw falſe Doctrines from them, it was at their own peril, and the fault was in their own giddineſs and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and not in the Word of God. They ſhould have only meddled with the plain Paſſages of them, which contain all things neceſſary to Salvation, and not with thoſe which are hard to be underſtood. No! if they had had a mind to underſtand the difficult Places of them, they ſhould have conſulted the Apoſtles, or thoſe whom the Apoſtles ſet over them, about the Apoſtolical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or Tradition; and if they did not, but, as ignorant men are apt to do, would precipitate themſelves into Errors, and make Doctrines to themſelves, which the Church never taught, that was their own fault, and could not without very much harm to Chriſtianity, ſuperſede the uſe of the Word of God. God in his great wiſdom intended it for the common Rule, or Canon of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Catholick Faith; and if unlearned men will be ſo head ſtrong, and Enthuſiaſtical, as not to try their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions by it, but it by their private Conceptions, it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs remains a Standard and Rule, and no leſs then their Souls muſt be the price for their Hereſies and Schiſms. The Devil underſtands this very well, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:62184:38"/>being a ſubtil and cunning Spirit, he is never want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to tempt Scioliſts, and men that want true Learning, eſpecially thoſe who are by nature powerfully enclined to Enthuſiaſm, to wreſt the Scriptures,<note n="*" place="margin">Sequamur uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitatem, anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitatem conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem. <hi>Vincent. Lirin.</hi> adverſus Haereſ. c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> againſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of univerſal Antiquity, to their own admired Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and that being done, it is no difficult matter to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them to ſet up for Teachers, altho' they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally need, that one teach them again, which be the firſt Principles of the Oracles of God, and are ſuch as have need of Milk, and not of ſtrong Meat.</p>
               <p>The ſecond ſort of Inſtruments by which Satan works, are over-curious, and over-inquiſitive men, who truſting too much to their own Underſtanding, love, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaks, to intrude into things which they have not ſeen, and are vainly puffed up with their fleſhly Mind.<note n="†" place="margin">De praeſcript. Haereſ. § <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in his Tract againſt the Hereſies of his Time, complains grievouſly of theſe men, who were always mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nice and curious Queſtions, about things which it was better to be ignorant of then to know, and who, as his phraſe imports, loved to exerciſe the<note n="‖" place="margin">Quantumlibet quaer as, &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes, &amp; omnem libidinem curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitatis eſſundas.</note> whole luſt of their Curioſity about doubtful and obſcure things. Their Curioſity, as he complains, was above their Faith, and their vain-glorious affectation of being counted learned and witty, above the care of their Souls; and therefore they muſt ſearch the Scriptures, to find out new Doctrines and Opinions, and if they cannot find them there, they will be ſure to bring them thither, tho' never heard of before, and never ſo contrary to the unanimous Tradition of all the Apoſtolical Churches. Theſe men he complains of, for the great Adulterators of Scripture; and of ſuch as they were, the Apoſtle is to be underſtood, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.4. I beſought thee to abide ſtill at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> that thou mighteſt charge ſome that they teach no other Doctrine, neither give heed to Fables, and endleſs Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogies, which miniſter Queſtions, rather then godly E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difying which is in the Faith. So in Chap. 6.3; 4. If any
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62184:39"/>man teach otherwiſe, and conſent not to wholeſom words, even the words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to the doctrine which is according to Godlineſs, he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited, knowing nothing, but doting about queſtions, and diſputes about words, whereof cometh envy, ſtrife, railings and ſurmiſings. So in his 2d. Ep. 2.23. ſaith he unto him, Avoid fooliſh and unlearned queſtions, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they gender ſtrife. And ſo in his Ep. to <hi>Titus,</hi> Chap. 2.9. Avoid fooliſh queſtions, and Genealogies, and contentions, for theſe are unprofitable, and vain, and a man that is an Heretick, after the firſt and ſecond admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion reject. Theſe over-curious and too inquiſitive Wits, who hunt after new Diſcoveries, and rack their Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as well as the Scriptures, to publiſh ſome new thing, are well diſpoſed by temper for Hereſie. They think in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they know ſomething, but really they know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as they ought to know, when they begin to deſpiſe the Simplicity of the Chriſtian Religion, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Tradition of the Elders, and by the wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Wits and Underſtandings, give occaſion to Satan, who obſerves all mens Tempers, to tempt them into Hereſie and Schiſm<note n="*" place="margin">— Longum eſt univerſa ipſus opera commemorare, quibus profecto ſummis Aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatoribus Eccleſtae par eſſe potuiſſet, niſi profanâ illâ <hi>haereticae curloſitatis libidine</hi> novum neſcio quid inveniſſet, quo &amp; cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctos labores ſuos velut cujuſdam Leprae ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixtione ſoedaret.—cap. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Vincenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Lirinenſis</hi> obſerves, that <hi>Apollinaris</hi> fell into Hereſie through this luſt of Curioſity; and that<note n="†" place="margin">Tantus, ac talis dum gratiâ dei inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiûs abatitur, dum <hi>ingenio ſuo nimium indulger,</hi> ſibi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſatis credit cum parvi pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit antiquam Chriſtiane religionis ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatem, dum ſe plus cunctis ſapere praeſumit, dum Eccleſiaticas traditiones, &amp; verterum magiſteria contemnens quaedam Scriptura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum capitula novo more interpretatur, meru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it ut de ſe quoque Eccleſia dei diceret. Si ſurrexerit in medio tui propbeta.—</note> 
                  <hi>Origen</hi> alſo, through too great a confidence in his own Parts, and too much fondneſs and indulgence for his own Notions, of the greateſt Doctor the Church ever had, became plainly ſuch a one, to whom one might juſtly apply thoſe words of <hi>Moſes, Si ſurrexerit in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio tui propheta,</hi> If there ariſe among you a Prophet—ſaying. let us go after other Gods, thou ſhalt not hearken unto the words of that Prophet, for the Lord your God proveth you,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62184:39"/>to know whether you love the Lord your God with all your heart and ſoul.</p>
               <p>The next ſort of Inſtruments which the Devil makes uſe of, in inventing and propagating Hercſie and Schiſm, are ambitious and aſpiring men, who would fain be Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours in the Church, and ſit in the Thrones of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; and when they cannot compaſs their Deſigns, then out of Envy and Revenge they ſtrive to turn all things topſie-turvy, and bring confuſion upon the Church. Such as theſe was <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> who loved to have the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence: He would fain have had St. <hi>John</hi>'s Chair, and to that end raiſed Sedition againſt him, prating againſt him with malicious words, and perſwading the Church not to receive him. Such alſo was <hi>Thebuthis,</hi> the firſt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick and Schiſmatick in the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as I have ſhewed in the firſt Chapter. Such alſo were <hi>Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Novatus, Arius, Natalis</hi> the Confeſſor, and almoſt all the famous Hereſiarchs in the ancient Church. Such alſo was <hi>Melitius,</hi> a Biſhop of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> who being depoſed from his Biſhoprick, for denying the Faith, and ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing unto <hi>Daemons,</hi> in the <hi>Diocleſian</hi> Perſecution, became the Head of that, which from him took the Name of the <hi>Melitian</hi> Hereſie and Schiſm. He loaded <hi>Achilles</hi> his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior, who depoſed him, with all manner of Calumnies and Reproaches; as alſo his Succeſſors, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xander,</hi> who ratified the Deprivation of him, and conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with <hi>Arius</hi> againſt the latter, that he might be reveng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Church. For Pride and Ambition is the Mother of Envy, Revenge and Diſcontent; it was the original Sin of the Devil, and when he meets with proud men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his own image, his work is half done, and it will coſt him but little trouble to tempt them to break the Peace, and divide the Unity of Churches, whereof they are Members. So an ancient<note n="*" place="margin">Reſponſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, quaeſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Author, in Anſwer to this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Whether it is juſt to damn Hereticks, who do their beſt Endeavours to know the Truth, and cannot: Saith
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62184:40"/>he, It is manifeſt that all Hereſies ariſe from a vain affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of Glory, and ſtudy of oppoſition in the Authors and Ring leaders of them; and therefore the Apoſtle calls them, grievous Wolves: And ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> in his firſt Homily upon the firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not love their Brethren, they envy thoſe that have a good Report, and from this Envy proceeds a deſire to be above them, and to rule, and from this deſire to rule come Hereſies. So ſaith <hi>Theophylact</hi> on <hi>Galat.</hi> 5. The deſire of Ruling is the Mother of all Hereſies: And ſaith another<note n="*" place="margin">Iſidorus Peluſiota, <hi>p.</hi> 441.</note> ancient Writer, From affectation of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and getting above others, which are two do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering Paſſions, I think moſt Hereſies ariſe, for thoſe who do not love to be in the rank of Subjects, ſow new Doctrines, that they may be Chief of a new Sect. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this was the temper of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> the firſt Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, and falſe Apoſtle; he affected to be a great man, and to have the People from the leaſt to the greateſt give heed unto him, as the great power of God: Though he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the Devil at his Baptiſm, yet he kept faſt hold of his Soul by this evil Affection, which was the gall of bitterneſs, that poiſoned his mind, the bond of iniquity whereby Satan held him, when he made him the firſt of his Apoſtles, the firſt of thoſe very Antichriſts, who in that Age of Miracles came after the working of Satan, with all power, and ſigns, and lying wonders, to deceive, if it were poſſible, the very Elect.</p>
               <p>The fourth ſort of Inſtruments which Satan employs, in making Diviſions and Schiſms, are covetous men, who love to be at the Head of a Sect, or Party, becauſe it is the ready way to get a good Maintenance, and become rich. There were ſuch as theſe in the Apoſtles days; as is plain from that notable paſſage, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.5. where he mentions perverſe diſputings of men of corrupt minds, and deſtitute of the truth, ſuppoſing that gain is Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and from ſuch (ſaith he) withdraw thy ſelf, for we
<pb facs="tcp:62184:40"/>brought nothing into this world, and it is certain we can carry nothing out. There were ſuch men as theſe in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> who made Parties among the People for their own ends, which gave the Apoſtle occaſion to rebuke them in words to this effect:<note n="*" place="margin">2. <hi>ep. cap.</hi> II. <hi>ver.</hi> 19, 20</note> As wiſe as you think your ſelves to be, you do with pleaſure, bear with fools, nay ye ſuffer worſe then fools, for you love men that bring you into bondage, you love men that devour you, and take Preſents of you, nay you love them, beſt that inſult over you, and as it were ſmite you on the face. So St. <hi>Jude</hi> tells us, That the Gnoſtical Hereticks ran gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily after the Error of <hi>Balaam</hi> for reward: And in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle's Epiſtle to <hi>Titus,</hi> we find him forewarning him of certain unruly and vain talkers, and deceivers whoſe mouths (ſaith he) muſt be ſtopped, who ſubvert whole houſes, teaching things which they ought not for filthy lucres ſake. So<note n="†" place="margin">2 <hi>Mand.</hi> 12.2.</note> St. <hi>Hermas,</hi> who was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Scholar, and wrote not long after him, ſpeaks of falſe Spirits in his Time, who received Reward for their Divination, and if they do not receive, (ſaith he) they do not continue long to propheſie. So<note n="‖" place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>H. E. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Montanus</hi> the Heretick, and falſe Prophet, after he had gathered a great concourſe of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple together, at the Place which he called the <hi>New Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> he appointed Collectors of Money, who under the Name of Offerings took Gifts and Preſents of the People, and his pretended Propheteſſes took not only Gold and Silver, but fine Cloaths, by way of Preſent; nay, ſaith <hi>Apollonius,</hi> thoſe who are called Prophets among the <hi>Montaniſts,</hi> take Money not only of the rich, but of the poor, and Orphans, and Widows; and therefore (ſaith he) either let them deny that their Prophets take Money, which we will prove by an hundred Teſtimonies, or elſe let them deny that they are true Prophets, becauſe they take Gifts. So I ſhewed in the firſt Chapter, that <hi>Natalis</hi> the Confeſſor was hired with Money to be a Biſhop of that schiſm in <hi>Rome,</hi> which taught, that Chriſt was a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:62184:41"/>meer man; ſaith the Hiſtorian of him, Being tempted with the Bait of Primacy among thoſe of that Sect, and of filthy Lucre which is the deſtruction of many men, he was ſcourged all night long by the holy Angels, and roſe betimes in the morning, and having put on Sackcloath and Aſhes, he went in great haſt, and with tears in his eyes caſt himſelf down before <hi>Zephyrinus</hi> the Biſhop, and fell down not only before the feet of the Clergy, but of the Laity alſo, and after much entreaty, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Stripes which he had received when he was a Confeſſor, he was admitted into the Communion of the Church. Before he was beaten by the Angels, our Lord frequently admoniſhed him of his Sin by Viſions in his Sleep, being unwilling that a Confeſſor for Chriſtianity ſhould periſh in Hereſie and Schiſm; but the love of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence and Money ſo bewitched him, that he was fain to uſe ſeverer Methods with him, and give him a Thorn in the Fleſh, before he would repent. He was conſtrained to laſh him out of the Circle in which he ſtood enchanted by the Devil, and as it were by force and violence break the double Chain of Ambition and Convetouſneſs, with which he had bound himſelf to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, and ſave him by a Miracle, as great as his Sin.</p>
               <p>The laſt ſort of men by which the Devil propagates and promotes Diviſions and Schiſms, are contentious and litigious men; as it is written by the Apoſtle, If any man be contentious, we have no ſuch cuſtom, nor the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God. I confeſs there is a contentious Diſpoſition, which is the effect of Ambition, and ſo is co-incident with the third particular Cauſe, which I aſſigned of Hereſie and Schiſm; but then there is a contentious Diſpoſition of another ſort, which proceeds from a ſophiſtical diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatious Humour, and a little ſort of pride in men, that makes them love to oppoſe and contradict every thing for contradictions ſake. This contentious Humour is moſt viſible in men who are hot and cholerick, and it natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:62184:41"/>puts them upon Controverſies and Diſputes, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Paradoxes, and calling received Doctrines into queſtion, and oppoſing things that are eſtabliſhed, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſit down and be quiet, it will be oppoſite to it ſelf, and be againſt that for which it was before. This reſtleſs, unquiet ſort of Spirit, hath bred much miſchief in all Societies, but eſpecially in the Church of God. It ſeems to me to have been the Temper of the Elder <hi>Arius,</hi> who as the<note n="*" place="margin">Socrat. <hi>l.</hi> I. <hi>c. 5.</hi>
                  </note> Hiſtorian tells us, was expert in Logical Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties and <note n="†" place="margin">Ex<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> out of a contentious humour oppoſed his Biſhop, diſcourſing a little too curiouſly about the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the holy Trinity. If this litigious humour at any time happen to be for the Truth, it is not out of love to Truth, but with a deſign to oppoſe others; as we read of ſome who preached the Goſpel, not out of good intent, but meerly to oppoſe the Apoſtle: Some indeed (ſaith he) preach Chriſt of meer envy and ſtrife, and ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of good will; the one preach Chriſt of contention, not ſincerely, ſuppoſing to add affliction to my bonds, but the other of love, knowing I am ſet for the defence of the Goſpel. To conclude, this litigious Humour is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in Greek by a word, which ſignifies the <hi>love of Contention,</hi> becauſe it is the delight and pleaſure of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious men, to be of a Party, and live in the duſt of Controverſie; they are no longer eaſie and happy, than they are engaged in ſome Quarrel: And therefore ſaith they are engaged in ſome Quarrel: And therefore ſaith <hi>Theophylact</hi> on <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.20. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>&amp;c. All Hereſie proceeds from the love of Contention, and the contentious perſon ſtriving to have his own will and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, doth thereby form a Schiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have I ſhewed the inſtrumental Cauſes which the devil uſes, in ſowing Differences and Diviſions, and making Separations and Schiſms in Churches: And per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of ſuch men, acted and inſpired by the Devil, as much as of the Devils themſelves, St. <hi>Peter</hi> is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, 1 Ep. 5.8. where he exhorted the Chriſtians to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:62184:42"/>be ſober, and vigilant, becauſe their adverſary the devil as a roaring lion walked about, ſeeking whom he might devour, whom (ſaith he) reſiſt, <hi>ſteadfaſt in the faith.</hi> If the Devil had ſo many Inſtruments of dividing the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church then, methinks it ſhould not ſeem ſtrange, that he hath ſo many now. Nay methinks the Gentlemen of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, out of the particular Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration they have for St. <hi>Peter,</hi> whom the whole Chriſtian World ought to honour, ſhould not ſo delight to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid the Church of <hi>England</hi> with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hereſies and Schiſms, it being evident from this and other Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in his Catholick Epiſtle, cited in the firſt Chapter, that there were almoſt as many, and altogether as great Diviſion, while he governed in the Church, as there are now in <hi>England,</hi> and moſt other Parts of the Chriſtian World.</p>
               <p>Wherefore all that can juſtly be concluded upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hereſies and Schiſms, if we conſider the inſtrumental Cauſes of them, is no more then this, That there are, and have been, many ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, over curious, ambitious, convetous, and contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men among us, which, as I ſhewed before, hath been the common Calamity of all Churches, and what is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all Churches, at leaſt according to our Logick, can be no juſt matter of reproach againſt any one. I am ſo confident, that there is no Inconſequence in this way of Apologizing for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that I believe our Adverſaries cannot find a better way of Apologizing for the Diviſions that have formerly riſen, or may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ariſe in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> If they were reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by others, as they reproach us, they could not but ſay, that the Cauſes of Diviſions are common to all Churches; and therefore craving leave to ſet the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the midſt of all other Churches, I deſire that Church may caſt the firſt Stone at her, which hath remained from the beginning a pure Virgin without He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:62184:42"/>or Schiſm. If there be a Church in any corner of the Earth, which is exempted from the common Cauſes of Diviſions, or of ſo happy a Conſtitution, as not to be capable of ſuffering by them, let that Church come forth, and reproach the Church of <hi>England</hi> with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hereſies and Schiſms; but let not the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> do it, which hath ſo many old Scars to ſhew, and ſo many and great Rents yet viſible in many parts of her Coat, as none of her moſt curious <hi>Workmen,</hi> with all their art and skill, will probably ever be able to make up.</p>
               <p>I have ſaid thus much by way of Apology for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> from conſidering the general Cauſes of Church Diviſions and Separations, and ſhall find yet more to plead for her, upon making a more particular Enquiry into the Cauſes of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hereſies and Schiſms. Now in this Enquiry, no man that knows the ſtate of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> betwixt the beginning of the <hi>great</hi> Rebellion, and his late Majeſty's happy Reſtauration, but muſt needs look upon the ruine of the Church and State, to have been ſuch a Cauſe of Hereſies and Schiſms, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps never happened before to any Church in the World. Was it any wonder to ſee Errors, and Hereſies, and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, abound among us, in a Time of ſuch ſtrange Diſorder and Confuſion, when there was no King, nor Prieſt in <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Can we imagine the Devil ſhould be idle in ſuch an Opportunity? Or can our Adverſaries imagine, that the like would not happen in any other Church or Kingdom of the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, ſhould God in judgment diſſolve the Government of them, as he did that of ours? I refer the candid <hi>Roman-Catholick</hi> Reader, to Mr <hi>Edwards</hi> his <hi>Gangraena,</hi> for an Account of the Errors. Hereſies, Blaſphemies, Sects, and Opinions, that ſprung up in the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Iſle, In a few years after the Church of <hi>England</hi> was pulled down, and her Liturgy caſt out of the Churches, and <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> as they called it, was ſet up in its ſtead. He was a Miniſter
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:62184:43"/>of the <hi>Presbyterian Party,</hi> and a mighty Bigot for the Cauſe, and yet he could not but acknowledge, that there came in a Deluge of Hereſies and Impieties after the removal of the <hi>Prelates;</hi> and I appeal to any man of Ingenuity, if it be Reaſonable, or Chriſtian, or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, to reproach our Church with Sects that aroſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, when ſhe was faſt bound in miſery, and the Iron entred into her Soul. Were not her Paſtors dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from their Flocks, when the Wolves entred in? and all the time ſhe was in the House of Bondage, was it not a time of Liberty for every man to do what was good in his own Eyes? Nay, I deſire thoſe that are moſt petulant in upbraiding us with our <hi>Diviſions,</hi> to tell me truly, if they do not think, that as many, and as monſtrous Swarms of Errours and Hereſies would breed in <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>Italy,</hi> as there did in the late Times of Confuſion in <hi>England,</hi> if the Divine Providence, (which God prevent) ſhould ſuffer the ſame Tragedy to be acted in thoſe Countries, that was acted in ours. How would Sects verminate any where in Twenty Years of ſuch Confuſion? Methinks our Adverſaries ſhould have the Ingenuity to conſider this; but ſince they ſeem not to do it, I hope they cannot find fault with us, for putting them in mind of it by way of Apology for our Church.</p>
               <p>There are many other ſpecial Cauſes of our <hi>Engliſh Diviſions,</hi> which might fall under conſideration, but for brevity ſake, I ſhall mention but one, which is this; That we have reaſon to ſuſpect that our <hi>Diviſions,</hi> both in the beginning and progreſs of them, may have been influenced from abroad. I do not know whether this will paſs for <hi>miſ-repreſenting,</hi> but ſome Obſervations have been made to this purpoſe. And if the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the <hi>R. Communion</hi> know or believe it to be true, I beſeech them by our Common Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> they would no longer upbraid the Church of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:62184:43"/>
                  <hi>England</hi> with the <hi>Engliſh Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Schiſms.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In <hi>Foxis and Firebrands,</hi> in <hi>Ravialac Redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinus,</hi> p 72. of the 2d. Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, fol. 1682. And in ſeveral Letters which paſſed between the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eminent perſons, which may be ſeen in a late printed Collection of Letters.</note> If the <hi>Tares</hi> which were ſowen in the Field of our Church were indeed brought from other Places, then I hope they will grant, that it is not ingenuous for them of all other <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to reproach us with them; but rather to blame thoſe who ſowed them, and who tranſplanted thoſe <hi>ſtrange Plants,</hi> which are not of our heavenly Father's planting, into the Vineyard of our Church. I confeſs it is very good Policy to divide us, that they may weaken us; but then it ſhould be remembred, that no Humane Policy, nor the greateſt Advantage that can follow upon it, can juſtifie the Dividing of any Church, though never ſo Heretical, by inventing new Doctrines. The <hi>Catholicks</hi> formerly durſt take no ſuch courſe to divide the <hi>Arians,</hi> they remembred that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathema</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> laid upon the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the very Angels of Heaven if they ſhould teach any other Doctrine; and I wiſh for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> others would do ſo too.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Cure of Schiſms and Diviſions.</head>
               <p>AFter this Enquiry into the Cauſes of <hi>Schiſms</hi> and <hi>Diviſions,</hi> and more particularly into thoſe of our own Country, I proceed to ſay ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Prevention and Cure of them; where, to keep cloſe to the deſign of my Apology for the Church, I muſt declare upon a ſerious reflection of what I have hitherto written, that I know no ſure and infallible way that is lawful, of preventing them, where they are not, or of curing them, where they are. Firſt then, I know no ſure way that is lawful of <hi>preventing</hi> of them, but ſome unlawful ways I confeſs there are, which are
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:62184:44"/>inconſiſtent with the Deſign of the Goſpel, and the Rules of Chriſtian Charity: but then the Remedy in ſuch caſes is worſe than the Diſeaſe; and accordingly we ſee that the ſtate of Chriſtianity is much more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable in ſome Countries, where Diviſions are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by ſuch methods, than in <hi>England,</hi> where no ſuch methods have been taken to prevent them: but of lawful and juſtifiable means, which are conſiſtent with the reputation and well-being of Chriſtianity, I believe there are none that will abſolutely prevent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and Schiſms: I confeſs Humane Fore-ſight and Diligence may, by God's bleſſing, prevent them in a great meaſure, but it will not always, nor altogether do ſo. But as Diſeaſes will happen to the Natural Body, notwithſtanding all the care and endeavours to prevent them: So <hi>Diviſions</hi> and <hi>Schiſms</hi> will happen to the Body Politick of Chriſt, and all the Parts and Members of it, notwithſtanding all that man can law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully do to prevent them; as is evident from the ſtate of the Church, while it was governed by the Apoſtles. For they were moſt holy, moſt wiſe, and moſt vigilant Paſtors, and therefore the greateſt holineſs and wiſdom of the moſt vigilant and diligent Paſtors, are not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to preſerve Unity, and prevent Schiſm. Nor are Miracles joyned with the Sanctity and Endeavours of the moſt vigilant Paſtors able to prevent it; for the Apoſtles and their Aſſiſtants wrought Miracles, and yet in the miraculous age of the Apoſtles, there were He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies and Schiſms, even in Churches where God bore them witneſs with Signs and Wonders, and divers Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles and Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt. Nay, Miracles are ſo far from having a Soveraign Vertue to prevent Schiſms, that in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> which abounded with miraculous Gifts, there were Envyings, Strifes, Contentions, and Diviſions: Nay, as I ſhewed in the Firſt Chapter, many of thoſe who had he gift of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62184:44"/>in the Apoſtles time, wilfully fell away from <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,</hi> to which they had born witneſs, and did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by deſpite unto the Spirit of Grace.</p>
               <p>And, as Miracles joyned with the utmoſt Sanctity, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Diligence of Paſtors, are not ſufficient to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent <hi>Diviſions;</hi> ſo neither is <hi>Infallibility</hi> added to all the reſt: for the moſt holy, the moſt wiſe, and moſt vigilant A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, were all infallible Judges certainly endow'd by God with the perſonal Gift of <hi>Infallibility;</hi> and yet in their time there were as many, and as great Hereſies and Schiſms, as perhaps have been ſince in any age of the Church. To uſe ſome of the emphatical words of another Author, every one of them was ſuch a Judge of Matters Spiritual, from which there needed no Appeal; every one of them had Authority and Ability to Interpret the Scriptures, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide in Matters of Conſcience, and yet there were as many Controverſies and Differences about Matters of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Religion then, as are now to be ſeen in <hi>England,</hi> or herhaps any other Country of the Chriſtian World. Do what the Apoſtles of the <hi>Circumciſion</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> could, they could not prevent the Enemy from ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Tares,</hi> nor the <hi>Tares</hi> from growing up, to the great prejudice and detriment of the <hi>Wheat:</hi> Hereſies and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences would come, notwithſtanding the <hi>Infallibility</hi> of <hi>S. John,</hi> who lay in our Lord's Boſom, and of <hi>S. James</hi> who was his Brother, and of <hi>S. Paul</hi> who was rapt into the third Heaven, and of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> to whom Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and upon this Rock I will build my Church.</hi> The <hi>R. Cs.</hi> may ſee from this little which I have ſaid, that if they had an infallible Judge, his Infallibility would be no certain Remedy againſt Hereſies and Schiſms, if they had no other ways that would not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der but that Diviſions might multiply among them as much as in the days of the Apoſtles, or as much as they are now multiplied in <hi>England,</hi> where the Church pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth to have no infallible Judge. I ſay, if they had
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:62184:45"/>an infallible Judge, his Infallibility would not be able to ſecure them againſt Diviſions but alas! they have no infallible Judge, for though they are all agreed, that their Church is <hi>infallible,</hi> yet they differ about the Seat of the <hi>Infallibility;</hi> they cannot tell us for certain where it is lodged: and truly to have an <hi>Infallible Judge,</hi> and not to know <hi>who,</hi> or <hi>where he is,</hi> is in effect to have none at all. What then, is there no certain way of preventing Hereſies and Schiſms? Certainly there is no lawful way certain; which Conſideration alone me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks might be Apology enough for the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> againſt the reproach which ſhe now ſuffers upon the account of the <hi>Engliſh Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Schiſms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as there is no certain way of preventing Hereſies and Schiſms where they are not: ſo there is no certain way of curing them where they are. Provincial and General Councils, where all emergent Differences may be freely and fairly debated, have by experience been found to be the beſt means which God hath been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to bleſs with ſucceſs; but tho' they are very good means, and have often proved very ſucceſsful, yet as we learn from the Hiſtory of Councils, they are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways infallible Remedies, as is evident from the firſt General Council, in which the Apoſtles and Elders, and Brethren met at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to determine whether or no it was needful for the Gentile Chriſtians to be Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed and keep the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> after much Diſpute on both ſides, firſt ſtood up, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, That to oblige the Gentile Diſciples to the <hi>Moſaical Obſervances,</hi> was to put a Yoak upon their Necks, which neither the <hi>Jews</hi> nor their <hi>Fathers</hi> were able to bear; then <hi>James</hi> having firſt heard <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared it was his ſentence, that the <hi>Gentile Christians</hi> ſhould be troubled with no more <hi>Jewiſh Obſervances,</hi> but to abſtain from Pollutions of <hi>Idols,</hi> from <hi>fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> from <hi>things ſtrangled,</hi> and from <hi>blood.</hi> To
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:62184:45"/>him the Apoſtles, and Elders, and the whole Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, and ſaid, it ſeemeth good to the holy Ghoſt, and to us, and yet the Authority of this infallible and unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Council, did not quite put an end to the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie: for, as it appears out of ſeveral of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, and more eſpecially out of that to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> &amp; ſome<note n="*" place="margin">Ad Magneſios, ad Philadelph.</note> Epiſtles of St <hi>Ignatius,</hi> there were thoſe afterwards who taught the <hi>Gentile</hi> Chriſtians Judaiſm, and commanded them to be circumciſed, and keep the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law. So I need not relate, how the oecumenical Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> tho' backed with the Authority of the Emperor, was not able to extinguiſh the <hi>Arian</hi> Schiſm, nor make the <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> acquieſce in its Determinations: And, to multiply no more Inſtances, the learned <hi>R. Cs.</hi> know very well, how far the Chriſtian World was from ſubmitting to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, which they call the ſeventh gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council, in its Determinations for Image-worſhip. Quite contrary the Northern and Weſtern Biſhops una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly oppoſed that Council, and its Doctrine; and in another<note n="†" place="margin">Concilium Franco ſurtes A. D. <hi>79<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> Council, wherein about 300 of them met together, they condemned it and its Decree for Image-worſhip, and proſcribed it out of the number of <hi>general Councils,</hi> and the Church of <hi>England</hi> at the Time was ſo far from acquieſcing in its Determinations, that her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors received that Decree for worſhipping of Images, with great indignation and contempt.</p>
               <p>But then, tho' it appears from theſe Examples, that general Councils are not infallible Remedies for Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Schiſms, yet it muſt be acknowledged, that they are very good ones, and the beſt that can be had, when they are truly<note n="*" place="margin">Cum dicunt Concilium: Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicum, aut univerſale, hoc intelligunt ut in eo debeant adeſſe viri pii, docti, &amp; prudentes ex omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nationibus. P. P. <hi>Vergerius</hi> in ſecretar. pontific. Act. primâ.</note> general and<note n="†" place="margin">Cum dicunt Liberum, volunt ut liceat tum publicis, tum privatis perſonis, ſub fide publici ſalvi conductûs praeſliti venire, ſtare, &amp; diſcedere, quoties illis libitum fuerit, &amp; ante omnia, ut liberè ſine ullo metu, aut impedimento loqui liceat, ſuam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſententiam dicere in ipſo Concilio. ibid.</note> free. And therefore as
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:62184:46"/>
                  <hi>Nilus</hi> of <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> propoſed a free and general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, as the beſt Expedient for ending all Differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Church above 300 years ago, ſo I hope I may without offence, propoſe it now, as the moſt hopeful Remedy to heal all Differences between the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> It would be an Enterprize worthy of the Greatneſs, and holy Character of the Pope, diſpenſing with the <hi>Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Oaths, to uſe his Intereſt among Chriſtian Princes, for the procuring of a free and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council, wherein<note n="*" place="margin">Statuerunt etiam quod amnes definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, &amp; concluſiones articulorum, de quibus ſuerit disputatum, ſierie debeant ex divinâ, &amp; ſacrâ Scripturâ, doctrinà<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> antiquorum patrum, &amp;. ibid. Scripturae eloquia aliter atque aliter, alius atque alius interpretatur, aliter nameque illam Novatianus, aliter Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus, aliter Sabellius, aliter Donatus expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit, aliter Arius, Eunomius, Macedonius, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Apollinaris, Priſcillianus, aliter Jovini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus, Pelagius, Caeleſtinus, aliter poſtremo Neſtorius, atque idcirco multùm neceſſe eſt propter tantos tam varii erroris anſractus, ut Prophetice. &amp; Apoſtolicae interpretationis linea ſecundum Eccleſiaſtici &amp; Catholici ſensûs normam dirigatur. <hi>Vincent Lirinenſ.</hi> adverſus haereſ. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> the holy Scriptures, and the Writings of the ancient Fathers, ſhould be laid open, and the Differences of the two Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches fairly tryed by them, as the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between <hi>Neſtorius</hi> and his Antagoniſts, was tryed in the third general Council. The Differences happened in the following manner. <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> openly taught, that it was not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to call the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or the Mother of God. This alarmed <hi>Cyrill</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and many other Biſhops, who ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that <hi>Neſtorius</hi> had a deſign, under the covert of that Aſſertion, to bring into the Church the Doctrine of <hi>Paulus Samoſatenſis,</hi> and <hi>Photinus,</hi> who aſſerted, that Chriſt was a meer man. Upon theſe Suſpicions they ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſed <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> and his Adherents, for their new Opinion, and the Contention grew ſo high, that the Emperor was fain to call a Council at <hi>Epheſus</hi> to compoſe it; and the Biſhops being met together, after ſome previ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Altercation, at laſt thought it the moſt Catholick, bleſſed, and deſirable way of determining the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, to produce the Opinions of the holy Fathers, who had been Martyrs, or Confeſſors for the Faith, or at leaſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:62184:46"/>had continued in the true profeſſion of it unto the end of their lives. Upon this were brought into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil the Writings of St. <hi>Peter</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> St. <hi>Theophilus,</hi> St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> St. <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzum, Gregorius Nyſſenus,</hi> St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and St. <hi>Foelix,</hi> and St. <hi>Julius,</hi> Biſhops of the Imperial City of <hi>Rome,</hi> with the Writings of other Fathers; all which being examined, it did appear that <hi>Neſtorius</hi> was an Innovator, and that <hi>Cyril</hi> was in the right, who ſaid, that the ancient Fathers uſed to call the Bleſſed Virgin, the <hi>Mother of God.</hi> I have taken this ſhort ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the manner in which the Council of <hi>Epheſus</hi> proceeded againſt <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> becauſe it is propoſed by<note n="†" place="margin">Quod ne praeſumptione magis noſtrâ quàm, autoritate Eccleſiaſticâ promere vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remur, exemplum adhibuimus Sancti Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilii, quod ante triennium fermè in Aſiâ apud Epheſum celebratum eſt, Viris clariſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis Baſſo Antiochoque conſulibus. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi cum ſanciendis ſidei regulis diſceptaretur ne qua illic forſitan prophana novitas in modum perfidiae Ariminienſis obreperet, univerſis Sacerdotibus, qui illo ducenti ſere numero convenerant <hi>hoc Cacholiciſſimum, faeliciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum atque optimum</hi> factu viſum eſt, ut in medium ſanctorum patrum ſententiae pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrentur, &amp;c. <hi>Vincent. Lirin.</hi> adverſus. haereſ. cap. <hi>42.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vincentius Liri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis,</hi> as the beſt method of ending Controverſies in Religion; and I am perſwaded, if the ſame Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal courſe was taken in a General Council now, the Differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Churches</hi> that diſſent from it, would come to an happy Concluſion, and by God's Bleſſing, make them all u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite into one <hi>Communion,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolical Church.</hi> I know very well that the Gentlemen of the <hi>Roman Communion</hi> are apt to tell us, that the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> was a Free and General Council, but we know the contrary, that it was neither Free nor General, or if it were, why may not the Church be repreſented a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new in another Free and General Council, as She was repreſented in the Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> ſhortly after the ſecond Council of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and in the ſecond Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> within thirty years after the ſeventh General Council of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which expreſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the <hi>Worſhip of Images?</hi> But they ſay the ſecond
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:62184:47"/>Council of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and the<note n="*" place="margin">This Council did not err in condemning the worſhip of Images.</note> ſeventh General Council <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> erred, and decreed falſe Doctrine: ſo ſay we of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and therefore let ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Free and General Council be called to umpire the Controverſie between the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent;</hi> and if upon a fair tryal by the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, Fathers</hi> and <hi>Councils,</hi> ſuch a Council ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> then I will leave her <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> and own I have been guilty of <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Schiſm.</hi> I think no Son of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> need ſcruple of ſay as much, nor fear to promiſe to ſtand to the Determinations of ſuch a Council, as will freely and impartially try all Controverſies by the ancient Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of<note n="†" place="margin">In Ipsâ ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicâ Eccleſiâ magnopere cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum eſt, ut id teneamus, quod ubi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quod ſemper, quod ab omnibus credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt.— Hoc ita demum fit ſi ſequamur <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nisverſitatem, Antiquitatem, Conſentionem. <hi>Vincent. Lirin.</hi> Cap. <hi>3.</hi> Vide etiam Cap. <hi>38.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality, Antiquity,</hi> and <hi>Conſent.</hi> This was the <hi>Catholick</hi> Teſt of old, and ought to be ſo ſtill, and to ſhew how indifferent I am between the two Churches: I heartily beſeech Almighty God that She may flouriſh and prevail, which is moſt willing to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo, and beſt able to abide this <hi>Teſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:62184:47"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>HAving now finiſhed the <hi>Apology,</hi> which I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to make for the <hi>Church of England,</hi> againſt thoſe who love to <hi>ridicule</hi> Her with the <hi>Engliſh Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> in Religion, and lay an heavy Charge of undue Conſequences upon her, meerly upon their ſcore: I think I cannot anſwer the Deſign of my Undertaking better, than in concluding with a practical and friendly Addreſs to the Candid <hi>READER,</hi> of what Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion ſoever, whether he be a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> or <hi>Church of England Catholick,</hi> or a <hi>Diſſenter</hi> from them both.</p>
               <p>I ſhall firſt begin with the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> who have been the occaſion of writing this Diſcourſe; and I humbly beg them to conſider, That it is not for their Honour to uſe ſuch Arguments againſt the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> now, as the <hi>Heathens</hi> of old uſed againſt <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity;</hi> nor for their Advantage to put us upon defending Her in the very ſame manner, as they muſt be forced to defend the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> againſt the <hi>Mahumetans,</hi> who are mightily prepoſſeſſed by the multitude of <hi>Sects</hi> among the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> againſt the Truth and Goodneſs of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> it ſelf, Nay, it is their Intereſt as much as ours, to leave off this way of Arguing againſt the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Scepticks,</hi> and irreligious perſons of both Churches argue the very ſame way againſt the Truth of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion;</hi> they take advantages from the great number and variety of <hi>Sects</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> whereof every on a pretends to be the <hi>true Church,</hi> to think that really there is no Religion; and therefore methinks all ſerious and piouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed perſons among the <hi>R. Cs.</hi> into whoſe hands this <hi>Apology</hi> ſhall fall, ſhould ſo far become my <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> as hereafter to forbear this way of Arguing, which gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifies.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:62184:48"/>the common Enemies of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes as ſeverely againſt the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church,</hi> as they would have it do againſt ours. Secondly, I deſire them to conſider, whether it be prudently done of them to reproach us with our Diviſions, when they do not know how ſoon we may have occaſion to turn their own <hi>Reproaches</hi> upon them, and do unto them, if <hi>Chriſtian Charity</hi> ſhould not reſtrain us, as they now do unto us. They do not know how ſoon their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> of which they boaſt ſo much, may be broken into <hi>Diviſions,</hi> and the <hi>Peace,</hi> which they pretend to have among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, be turned into a <hi>ſpiritual War.</hi> The Spirit of <hi>Strife</hi> and <hi>Contention,</hi> and of ſetting up <hi>Altar</hi> againſt <hi>Altar,</hi> may, for all their preſent aſſurance, come upon them, as <hi>ſorrow upon a Woman in travail;</hi> and then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Sects,</hi> which ſhall ariſe among them, be real, or only reputed <hi>Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Schiſms,</hi> they will be taken in their own <hi>Snare,</hi> and the full weight of their own <hi>Arguments</hi> againſt us, will fall upon their own heads. Let him that thinketh the <hi>ſtandeth</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) take heed leſt the <hi>fall;</hi> and let the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> which perhaps the <hi>R. Cs.</hi> may think ſo ſecure in her <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> take heed ſhe fall not into pieces, and be broken in ſhivers like a <hi>Potters Veſſel,</hi> by him that ruleth with an <hi>Iron Rod.</hi> They ſhould conſider that God can ſend the Spirit of <hi>Luther</hi> upon their <hi>Monks,</hi> the Spirit of <hi>Savanarola</hi> upon their <hi>Fryars,</hi> the Spirit of <hi>Herman</hi> and <hi>Cranmer</hi> upon their <hi>Prelates;</hi> the Spirit of <hi>Vergerius</hi> &amp; <hi>Contarenus</hi> upon their Nuncio's and Legates; the Spirit of Cardinal<note n="†" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Vergerii</hi> Annotat, in Catal, Heret. <hi>261, 262.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Fregoſius</hi> upon the <hi>Conclave;</hi> the Spirit of<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Of</hi> Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</note> 
                  <hi>Albert</hi> &amp;<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Of</hi> Saxony.</note> 
                  <hi>Frederic</hi> upon Soveraign Catholick Princes; and the Spirit of <hi>Marcellus ſecundus</hi> upon the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf. They ſhould remember, eſpecially the Learned among them, from what a ſlight accidental occaſion, the <hi>Arian Schiſm</hi> began; and God who was pleaſed to ſuffer an <hi>univerſal Conflagration to ariſe from
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:62184:48"/>ſuch a ſmall Spark, can in a moment raiſe up many <hi>Arius</hi>'s <hi>Rome,</hi> and make the Princeſs of the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſit ſolitary,</hi> and all her <hi>Friends</hi> become her <hi>Enemies.</hi> Nay, he is able, as it were, by a Voice from Heaven, to ſay unto her people, <hi>Come out of her, leſt ye be partakers of her ſins.</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Saltem <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarchae</hi> parce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, Praeſertim cum fuerit ex praelatorum nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero parumque abſuerit, ut à <hi>Benedicto XII.</hi> fuerit Cardina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis creatus— Homo Italus at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que idem ex praecipuis Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latis unus, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ Eruditione, &amp; ſapientiâ vir, quem Papa, quem tota Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolica Sedes, quem tota Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia maximi fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit atque colit. <hi>PP. Vergerius</hi> Annot. in Catal. Haer. fol. <hi>259, 260.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Petrarch</hi> one of her moſt Eminent Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in <hi>Proſe</hi> and <hi>Verſe,</hi> who was the Pride and Glory of <hi>Italy,</hi> and the Delight of <hi>Rome,</hi> where he received the Laurel; <hi>Petrarch</hi> one of her <hi>Celebrated Church-men,</hi> who narrowly miſſed a <hi>Cardinal</hi>'s <hi>Cap;</hi> the Learned, the Eloquent, the Charming <hi>Petrarch</hi> applied this, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more ſuch Texts unto Her in an<note n="*" place="margin">Part of which Epiſtle is tranſlated and cited by <hi>Vergerius. Ibid. fol.</hi> 259, 260.</note> 
                  <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> wherein he Paraphraſed the 17th. Chapter of the <hi>Revelations;</hi> and how do they know, but God may make the people hear, and obey the Voice of <hi>Petrarch,</hi> and come out of her in as great numbers beyond the <hi>Alps</hi> and <hi>Apen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nines,</hi> as they have done on this ſide of them. The <hi>Pectilent Northern Hereſie,</hi> as one called it, may ſoon <hi>ſcale the Mountains,</hi> and invade the <hi>Southern Climates,</hi> and they themſelves do not know how ſuddenly God may make <hi>Province</hi> after <hi>Province,</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi> after <hi>Nation,</hi> fall off and ſeparate from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> What hath been done, may be done again; and upon ſuppoſition this ſhould happen, I would fain know of from the <hi>Roman Communion,</hi> would be a good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the <hi>Trueneſs</hi> or <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> Wherefore methinks is point of Prudence, they ſhould not take up Arguments againſt us, which they do not know how ſoon we may have occaſion to retort upon themſelves. They ſhould remember that they cannot ſecure their <hi>Church</hi> againſt <hi>Contigencies,</hi> that are common to all <hi>Churches,</hi> and that to fleſh ſhould glory in the preſence of God, who ſometimes chooſes the <hi>weak things</hi> of the World, to <hi>confound the mighty;</hi> and <hi>things that are not,</hi> to bring to nought
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:62184:49"/>
                  <hi>things that are.</hi> It is his Prerogative to do whatſoever he pleaſeth in <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth;</hi> and who knows his <hi>Counſels?</hi> who knows what <hi>ſecrets of Providence</hi> are in the <hi>Wombs</hi> of their <hi>Cauſes</hi> ready for the <hi>birth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place, I addreſs my ſelf to our <hi>diſſenting Brethren,</hi> whoſe Diviſions and Separations from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and from one another, are now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come popular and plauſible Arguments in the mouths of the <hi>R. Cs.</hi> to unſettle weaker judgments among us, and bring them over to <hi>theirs,</hi> which they call the <hi>one Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church.</hi> I beſeech them therefore by the Sacred Names of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> to conſider ho'w different the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and her <hi>Children</hi> now appear, from what they miſ-apprehended them to be. Great numbers of them took up an <hi>Averſion</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they thought her <hi>Popiſh</hi> in her <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and her Children, eſpecially the <hi>Clergy,</hi> Popiſh in their Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: but now ſeeing by Experience how much they were miſtaken, methinks they ſhould be willing to make Reparation; methinks the ſenſe of their <hi>former miſtake,</hi> ſhould help to overcome their <hi>preſent prejudice,</hi> and make them willing to be better informed, and bring their old <hi>Scruples,</hi> with Minds deſirous of <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> to the <hi>Teſt;</hi> to ſee if indeed they are ſuch as will juſtifie their <hi>ſeparation</hi> from a <hi>Church,</hi> which they acknowledge to be Orthodox in her <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and which they could never yet prove enjoyned any one thing in her <hi>Worſhip,</hi> which God and forbidden, or to have forbidden any thing in it, which he had enjoyned, Is not this the time for them to peruſe the Books that have been lately writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the greateſt Candor and meekneſs for their bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Information? And doth not the <hi>Zeal,</hi> which they have always profeſſed againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> oblige them to have a good opinion of her <hi>Divines,</hi> who have all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long been contending earneſtly for the <hi>Faith</hi> which was once delivered to the <hi>Saints?</hi> Doth not God by the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:62184:49"/>Voice of his Providence call upon them, as plainly as if it were by a Voice from Heaven, to conſider whither their Diviſions tend, and ſhould not the ſerious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the diſmal Effects that may follow upon them, if they continue in them, make them doubly afraid of the ſinfulneſs of Schiſm? What a dreadful account will they have to make at the Day of Judgment, if it ſhould then appear, that the Church gave them no juſt occaſion to ſeparate from her? They muſt then anſwer to God for all the direful Conſequences of their Separation; and therefore it concerns them all to look upon her whom they have pierced; it concerns them all, as they would not die in ſo fatal a Miſtake, and be reſponſable for the downfal of the Church, to examine impartially, if the Communion of the Church of <hi>England</hi> be not truly Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, and whether ſhe is not ſuch a Church, as hath fellowſhip with the Father, and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>If ſhe be ſuch a Church, as the Divines of all reformed Churches abroad will tell them ſhe is, then they muſt be guilty of Schiſm, which is a ſeparation without a juſt cauſe from the Church, as a Church, without any regard unto the State. For Schiſm or Separation, without a juſt cauſe, is a pure ſpiritual Crime, and was reckoned a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Sin, before the Church Chriſtian was united to the Empire, as alſo in thoſe unhappy Intervals of Perſecution, when the Church and Empire were diſ-united again. For example, it was a damnable Sin, when St. <hi>Paul</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace, becauſe there was but one God, and one Lord and one Faith, and one Baptiſm, and one Body of Chriſt. It was a damnable Sin, when he told the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> That we were all baptized by one Spirit into one body, and that as the natural body was made one by the union of many members in it, ſo alſo was the body, meaning the Body politick of Chriſt. It was a damnable Sin, when St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> taught the Churches, That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:62184:50"/>ſhould be done without the leave of the Biſhop, or in oppoſition to him, and that, that was only a valid Euchariſt which was adminiſtred by him, or by one li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed and appointed by him, and that makers of Schiſm could not inherit the Kingdom of God. It was a damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sin, when St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> called private Meetings, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the publick, Conventicles of the Devil; and ſaid, that private Altars were no Altars; and that if a Schiſmatick ſhould die for Chriſt, he could be no Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, nor have any right to the Crown of Martyrdom; for which he alledges the words of the Apoſtle, Tho' I give my body to be burned, and have not charity, it proſiteth nothing. <hi>Dionyſius Alexandrinus</hi> in his Ep. to the Arch-Schiſmatick <hi>Novatus,</hi> writes unto him in this manner. <hi>If thou waſt conſtraind, as thou ſaiſt, againſt thy will, to ſeparate from the Church, thou oughteſt to declare the ſame, by returning willingly to it again. Thou ſhouldſt have ſuffered any thing rather then rend the Church of God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is that Martyrdom, which a man ſhall ſuffer for refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to rend the Church, leſs glorious, then that which Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians daily ſuffer for denying to ſacrifice unto Devils. Yea, in my judgement, it is a more glorious ſort of Martyrdom, for in the one a man ſuffers Martyrdom only for his own Soul, but in the other for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church. Wherefore perſwade the Brethren, or conſtrain them to return to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſuch a meritorious act would be greater then the crime of ſeducing them, and thou wouldeſt be more commended for that, then ever thou wert cenſured for this. However if thou canſt not perſwade the rebellious and diſobedient to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Church, at leaſt ſave thine own ſoul, by embracing Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity thy ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So great a Sin did the ancient Fathers account Schiſm, before the happy union of the Church and Empire, when the Meetings of the Schiſmaticks were as much tolerated by the State, as the Meeting of the Catholicks; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame Principle, <hi>Donatiſm</hi> and <hi>Arianiſm</hi> were
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:62184:50"/>counted as damnable Schiſm every jot, under the Reigns of thoſe Emperors, who granted toleration to them, as under the Reigns of thoſe who made Laws againſt them. Nay, all the Laws which <hi>Conſtantius</hi> and <hi>Valens</hi> made in favour of <hi>Arianiſm,</hi> and for the eſtabliſhment of it, did not alter its damnable nature in the judgement of the Catholicks; neither indeed is the obliquity of Schiſm al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable by humane Laws and Conſtitutions, as being a tranſgreſſion of a divine poſitive Law, which God hath made for the preſervation of the Body politick of his Church, to which Schiſm is as deſtructive in its nature, as Rebellion is to the State.</p>
               <p>The being and well-being of the Church are incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible with it, and it is not only evil becauſe God hath forbid it, but God hath forbid it becauſe he knew it was evil, and pernicious in its nature to his <hi>one</hi> Catholick Church. The <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> themſelves will joyn with us in this Principle, and acknowledge this Doctrine to be true, and if our Diſſenters are either afraid, or convinced of the truth of it, it concerns them, as they tender their own Salvation, to enquire into the nature of their reſpective Separations, whether they the Schiſms, or no? They all profeſs great tenderneſs of Conſcience, and they will but act according to their pretenſions, to be very ſcrupulous in embracing thoſe Communions; which, if they be not, yet look ſo like Schiſm. Methinks they ſhould be as much afraid of ſinning one way as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; methinks their Conſciences ſhould boggle as much at a ſuſpected Communion, as at a ſuſpected Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and be very much afraid of making damnable Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, as they will aſſuredly do, if the Church of <hi>England,</hi> from which they do, or ſhall ſeparate, be a true and ſound Member of Chriſt I entreat them for the ſake of their own Souls, to ſet the Terror of this Conſequence before their eyes; eſpecially I deſire thoſe among them to conſider it, who by their <hi>occaſional</hi> Communion (as
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:62184:51"/>they call it) with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> have declared to all the World, that they think if ſuch a Church, to which men may joyn themſelves without ſin. Shall the expectation of a little temporary Preferment, or the fear of a little temporal Puniſhment, bring them to Church, and perhaps to the higheſt act of Communion in it, and ſhall not the fear of Damnation, and the foreſight of the diſmal Events, which are like to happen upon their Separations, not make them do the ſame? If it be ſinful to communicate with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, why did they ever do it? And if it be not, why do they not do it always, according to the Doctrine of the Apoſtle, who beſeeched the <hi>Corinthians</hi> by the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that they ſhould all ſpeak the ſame thing, and be perfectly joyned together in the ſame mind and judgement, that there ſhould be no Schiſms nor Diviſions among them. I beſeech our diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, by the ſame ſaving Name, and for the ſake of the Goſpel, for which they pretend to have ſo much zeal, not to divide Chriſt any longer among us, nor grieve the holy Spirit of Union by their cauſleſſ Separations, but to return to the Fold from which they have wandred as loſt Sheep, that ſo we may become one Fold under one Shepherd, and one Building framed together into an holy Temple unto the Lord. They know there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanting to any Chriſtian man's Salvation in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> they may be as holy and unblamable in the Communion of it, as the moſt holy Saint, or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, if it be not their own fault; and certainly <hi>Jacob</hi> would rejoyce, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> would be glad, may I dare ſay, there would be joy among the very Angels in Heaven, to ſee them return to their Mother, whom they have forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and compaſs her Altars in Sincerity and Truth. This would be the way for them to atone for their former Maſcarriages, and undo all the Injuries they have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done the Church, which upon their Return would be
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:62184:51"/>beautiful as <hi>Tirzah,</hi> comely as <hi>Jeruſalem,,</hi> and terrible as an Army with Banners, and provoke her Adverſaries, who now inſuit over her Diviſions, to confeſs, that ſhe is the very Beauty of Holineſs, and that God was in us and among us of a truth.</p>
               <p>In the laſt place I addreſs my ſelf to my Brethren of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for whoſe Satisfaction I have written this Apology, That ſeeing how Hereſies, Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Schiſms, have been incident to the beſt Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, in the beſt and pureſt Ages, the Age of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and the Age next unto them, they ſhould neither be offended nor diſcouraged, to ſee ſo many Altars erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this little Iſle, all oppoſite to one another, and to the Church. I have ſhewed them, that her condition is neither new, nor ſingular, and that as many and great Diviſions have been made from the Churches of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Antioch, Alexandria, Conſtantinople, Rome, Carthage,</hi> and all the famous Churches in the World. Nay, I have ſhewed more particularly of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that very ſhameful and ſcandalous Schiſms have formerly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſen in her, and that not withſtanding her pretended preſent Union, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the midſt of all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Diviſions, hath more potential and actual Union then ſhe, I have had good ſucceſs in private, with a ſhorter Diſcourſe of this nature, in confirming of ſome, who began to have mean and deſpicable thoughts of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> upon the ſcore of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Schiſms, and to ſuſpect whether or no the were a true and good Church. They were made believe, of all Churches ſhe was moſt deſerted by God, and that he ſeemed to have very little ſavour for her; and then while they were caſting about for Reaſons, why God ſhould ſeem, as they were taught, to have ſo little care of her, it was eaſily ſuggeſted, that he was diſpleaſed at her, and left her to her ſelf, becauſe ſhe had left the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And as I have known ſome, ſo I have heard of others, who
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:62184:52"/>have been juſt ſo affected; and it is for curing ſuch Fears and Suſpicions where they are, and preventing them where they are not, that I have made this Apology, which I hope my Brethren will accept, as a Work well intended, with all its imperfections and defects. I know it is but a very indifferent Performance, in compariſon to what others have done, and are a doing; but ſuch as it is, I offer it with all ſubmiſſion to the whole Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of God, in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which as it now ſtands without any farther emendation, is, I verily) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, as ſound and pure a Church, both for Doctrine and Worſhip, as ever was eſtabliſhed in any Province, or Nation of the World, I heartily thank Almighty God, by whoſe good providence I have been bred up in her Communion, and am called to the great Honour of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of her Prieſts; and I beſeech him of his infinite goodneſs, to give all her Clergy, and People, Grace, to live up ſtrictly to her Principles; to her Principles of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards God, of Loyalty to the King, of Juſtice and Charity to others, and of Temperance and Sobriety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards themſelves. I am ſure it muſt be ours, and not her fault, if we be not the beſt Chriſtians, the beſt Subjects, and the beſt Friends and Neighbours in the Worlds; and I ſhall confirm my own Opinion of her, with the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony which a late<note n="*" place="margin">S. L. J.</note> great, and good, and learned Man, gave of her in his laſt Will and Teſtament, ſaith he, <hi>I do declare, That by the grace of God, I die a Chriſtian in the Communion of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>as it is now eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God's Providence, and the Laws in force; I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this Church to be a true and ſound Member of Chriſt's Catholick Church, which he hath purchaſed with his Bloud. Cloath her, O Lord, with a ſtrict and examplary Holineſs in her Priests and People, and maintain her in her Truths, Peace, and Patrimony, unto the Worlds end.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:62184:52"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
